<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The best entail, or, Dying parents living hopes for their surviving children grounded upon the covenant of Gods grace, with believers and their seed, being a short discourse upon 2 Sam. 23, 5 : wherein is a collection of several covenant-promises to support the faith, and some pleas to direct and quicken the prayers of Gods covenanted people for their surviving posterity / by O.H. ...</title>
            <author>Heywood, Oliver, 1629-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 176 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43572</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1761</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40552</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19356469</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19356469</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108774</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43572)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108774)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1672:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The best entail, or, Dying parents living hopes for their surviving children grounded upon the covenant of Gods grace, with believers and their seed, being a short discourse upon 2 Sam. 23, 5 : wherein is a collection of several covenant-promises to support the faith, and some pleas to direct and quicken the prayers of Gods covenanted people for their surviving posterity / by O.H. ...</title>
                  <author>Heywood, Oliver, 1629-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 69 [i.e. 96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [16].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 2nd, XXIII, 5 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Covenant theology.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108774:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108774:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Beſt Entail.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR, Dying Parents Living Hopes for their ſurviving Children, grounded upon the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Gods Grace, with Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers and their Seed.</p>
            <p>BEING A ſhort Diſcourſe upon 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN Is a Collection of ſeveral Covenant-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to ſupport the Faith, and ſome Pleas to direct and quicken the Prayers of Gods Covenanted People for their ſurviving Poſterity.</p>
            <p>By <hi>O. H.</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 90.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Let thy Work appear unto thy Servants, and thy Glory unto their Children.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:108774:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108774:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY.</head>
            <head type="sub">To the Right Honourable <hi>Philip</hi> Lord <hi>Wharton.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe concernedneſs your Lordſhip, hath for the worthy Branches of your Noble Family, is demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated to all whom you eſteem Friends, by the conſtant ſubſcription with your own hand [Remember me and my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily in your Prayers,] by which your Lordſhip at once teſtifies your natural Affection and true Piety: Your earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the beſt good, and the means by which that muſt come from God, even duon the wings of a believing Prayer.
<pb facs="tcp:108774:3"/> Your Lordſhips requeſt hath the force of a command; the obligations laid upon many hundreds of both Miniſters and People, extort from us, in point of Gratitude, both many thankſgivings to God, and renewed ſupplications for your Lordſhip, that the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham,</hi> may ſucceſſively continue in your Noble Family, to be bleſſed, and be a bleſſing. Oh happy Family! where the precious Pearl of Covenant grace Enamels the Gold-ring of worldly honour! 'Tis true, the Divine Oracles ſay, Not many Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not many Noble are called. A good Lady added, Bleſſed be God, that it ſaith not [not any.] Once at laſt God will have an Emperour [a <hi>Conſtantine</hi>] ſaved. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith wittily, a poor <hi>Lazarus</hi> is laid in rich <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſom. Sacred Writ records a Noble <hi>Theophilus,</hi> and an Elect Lady: And Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory furniſheth us with a large Catalogue of Illuſtrious Branches of Noble Families, planted in the Houſe of the Lord, and, like fixed Stars of the firſt Magnitude, have ſhined bright in their proper Orb, and conveyed great Influence to their Inferiours. In which rank God hath placed your Honour; whoſe Morning
<pb facs="tcp:108774:3"/> Star of early Piety continues ſtill ſhining bright to a good old Age, and hath caſt many reſplendent Beams of favour upon Indigent Perſons, to ſpread the favour of Divine Knowledg amongſt ignorant ſouls in the Country; for which the loyns of the Poor, and ſouls of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed will bleſs you in this, and the other world. I doubt not, my Lord, but your gracious ſpirit Eccho's to the dying ſpeech of holy <hi>David,</hi> to whom a ſucceſſion of Piety in his ſeed was more Eligible than of Royalty and large Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues. What can be compared to this one comprehenſive promiſe, <hi>[I will be a God unto thee, and to thy ſeed after thee:]</hi> Yet this is the rich priviledg of Gods Covenanted Servants: Mines of Gold, Mountains of Pearl, can bear no proportion to this one word [My God:] This is light in darkneſs, life in death, an heaven in the midſt of hell. The ſenſe of this is the only Cordial to the fainting Spirits of Gods afflicted Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Yea, ſaith one, if but one little drop of Divine Love, ſhould fall into a Damned Soul in Hell, it would ſweeten or ſwallow up thoſe bitter Torments. And next to the priviledg of Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:108774:4"/> our God; His being our Childrens God claims the Preeminence: For Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents anxious thoughts run out for their Childrens well-doing in this and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world. If God help us to own him, he will not forſake us or ours. It's true Grace comes not by ſucceſſion, yet oft in ſucceſſion. The Line of Covenant-love reacheth to many Generations; and the more numerous pious Predeceſſours are, the greater is the ſhower of Bleſſings. So a Learned man reads that paternal benediction of <hi>Jacob</hi> to <hi>Joſeph,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 49.26.</note> 
               <hi>The bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of thy Fathers are ſtrong with the bleſſings of my Progenitours:</hi> As the more waters run into one Channel, the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per it grows. Your Lordſhip then may hope for multiplied, accumulative bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings on your Noble Progeny. If that be found Divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty, which was a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xime amongſt the Jewiſh Rabbies, That the Divine Glory reſts on Noble Stemms; however beams of love reflect with great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt luſtre when deſcending on honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Perſonages. Therefore ſhould we pray, moſt ardently, for thoſe of higheſt rank, as in the greateſt capacity of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſt good; and a godly man, or Miniſter, muſt not only, with <hi>David,
<pb facs="tcp:108774:4"/> ſerve his own generation by the will of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 13.36.</note> but with the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.15.</note> 
               <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour that poſterity may be able after their deceaſe to have Divine Truths al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in remembrance.</hi> This, my Lord, hath been the great care of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; and as natural motions are quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt towards the end, ſo the nearer your Lordſhip approacheth to your center, and Haven, the more ſedulous and active are you to lay a foundation of Religion in future Generations; thereby alſo lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up in ſtore for your ſelf a good foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for time to come,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.19.</note> ſo laying hold on Eternal Life, for the accompliſhing of this great End. A poor inconſiderable worm caſts his Mite into my Lords Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury and proſtrates himſelf at your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Feet, in this Dedication, in teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of my real gratitude for your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallel'd kindneſs and condeſcention to ſo ignoble a perſon. Withal recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this ſmall Treatiſe to your Lordſhip, to encourage your heart, and ſtrengthen your hands in God, under the ſmarting breaches in your Noble Family; ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing it into a critical world under your Lordſhips auſpicious Name: not doubting a pardon of this boldneſs, and
<pb facs="tcp:108774:5"/> a candid acceptance following it, with my poor Prayers, that it may obtain its deſired ſucceſs upon the riſing Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and provoking Parents to improve this bleſſed Covenant; hoping that when your Lordſhip hath filled up your days with Grace, and tranplanted your Soul into the Coeleſtial Paradiſe; ſome of your Seed ſhall riſe up in your room as Plants of Renown, to bear your Image and Name, and follow your gracious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample while Sun and Moon endure: Which is the daily Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your humble and devoted Servant,</hi> Oliver Heywood.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:108774:5"/>
            <head>A PREFACE, OR AN EPISTLE to the READER.</head>
            <p>THere is nothing in the World (I am very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident) lyes ſo near the heart of a gracious Chriſtian, next to the Glory of God and his own Souls Eternal happineſs, as the Spiritual good of his dear Children: nature binds him to love his own: Chriſtianity regulateth and Spiritualiſeth this love: fondneſs is not true love, but faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: love to their bodies is but bruitiſh without love to their Souls: i'ts like a doting on the Caſe, and throwing away the Jewel, the Soul is the man, the unſeen part is the beſt part; where the Soul is lodged, when parted from the Body, there muſt the Body lodg, in Heaven or Hell: Oh that men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood and well digeſted this! ſurely they would not ſo unweariedy toil and tread to get Eſtates for their Children, and take no care of their preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Souls, and know not when they Dye whether <hi>he that comes after them ſhall be a Wiſe man or a Fool:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 21.9</note> if he be a wiſe man, a little will ſerve him, with Gods bleſſing: if wicked he puts a Sword into the hand of a Fool to do himſelf and others a greater miſchief: Oh how much better is it for their own peace and their Childrens profit to plead the Covenant, to Inſtruct, Correct, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh,
<pb facs="tcp:108774:6"/> Counſel, Comfort and incourage their Children in the ways of God, and uſe their utmoſt Endeavour to make them Gods Children: an Ancient thus writes,<note place="margin">Sabrian ad Eccleſ. <hi>cath.</hi> lib. 3. p. 441.</note> 
               <hi>[Diſciplinam parentes deus jubet theſauriſare filijs, non pecuniam, perennia praecipit non peritura conferre]</hi> God commands Parents to hoard up Diſciplin, not Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for their Children, things of a perpetual not periſhing nature: what a baſe and ſordid thing is it to prefer a Swine to a Son! to provide for a Beaſt and caſt out a Child! and yet moſt Parents beſtow more care of their Cattel than of their Childrens Souls: they give their Children nature, but deny them nurture: Yea they propagate cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption to them, but do not travel over them till Chriſt be formed in them: they glory in being Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of their Fleſh, but cry not to the Father of Spirits for the beſt life in their Childrens dead Souls: they promiſe at their Baptiſm, to bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord, but know not what that meaneth, and have no heart to learn, that they may teach: Oh what account will theſe perjured Parents give another day? Remember God will call you to account, what Anſwer will you give, when he ſhall Say? where is the Childs Soul, that I committed to thy truſt? what care haſt thou taken of it? where are thy Tears, Prayers, Groanings, Earnings of Bowels for thine own Bowels? didſt thou not know that thy Child had a Soul? that its Soul was polluted with Sin? that it muſt be born again not only of Water but of the Spirit: or could not be Saved? that though I was to be the Efficient cauſe, yet thou muſt be the Inſtrument to begin and carry on this
<pb facs="tcp:108774:6"/> Work, and haſt thou ſtruck one ſtroke in this work by faithfull endeavours? or haſt thou ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſired me to do that for thy Child that thou couldeſt not? thou knoweſt thou haſt done neither, and therefore thy Childs Blood ſhall be reqiured at thy hands: what Apology wilt thou then make for thy ſelf? Doſt thou think to come off by Saying, I ſent him to School to learn, or to the Miniſter to be Catechiſed? this is more than ſome will do, but is this all? is not paternal care thy perſonal duty? was not thou charged with thy Childs Soul? may not God juſtly blaſt other teachers pains as a puniſhment of thy negligence? and doth not thy bad Example at home unravel all that others teach them? Wo, Wo be to ſuch wicked wretched Parents!</p>
            <p>In the name of God I charge you, as you will not have your Children accuſe and curſe you in Hell for ever, concern your ſelves deeply about their Everlaſting State, think they can never do well, if they do not well for another World: they will never be dutifull to you, till they be Obedient to God: train them up for God and you conſult at once Gods Glory, the good of Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, your own Comfort, and their Eternal felicity: true Grace qualifys perſons for every condition: for he that is really good will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latively good: a good King and Subject, Father and Child, Maſter and Servant: Heathens knew this, that the way to form Perſons into a due mould of civil Subjection is a literate and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Education: thus the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering <hi>Judah,</hi> ordered the Kings ſeed,<note place="margin">Dan. 1.3, 4</note> and Princes to be trained up in the <hi>learning of of the
<pb facs="tcp:108774:7"/> Chaldeans:</hi> and our own Hiſtorys tell us, that when the <hi>Romans</hi> conquered this Iſland, <hi>Julius Agricola</hi> brought Noble mens Sons to <hi>Rome,</hi> and cauſed them to be educated in liberal Sciences, whereby they gradually tamed the furious temper of the <hi>Brittains,</hi> ſo that the Inhabitants here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came of gentle ſpirit, and peaceable Subjects: much more will Chriſtianity and true Piety, bring perſons into a regular conformity: it expells Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barity and produceth Civility, Hoſpitality, Fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality, and yet a diſcreet liberality: a divine Benediction is entailed upon Sincere Religion: <hi>Godlineſs is profitable unto all things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>having promiſe of the life that now is and of that which is to come:</hi> if your Children be Godly they will be fit for any thing, and all things will conduce to their good:</p>
            <p>And You, Oh children, ſuffer a word of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation from one that hath had Experience of childhood, Youth, riper age, and is arrived at old age, and hath been a teacher of others above forty years, and may ſay to you as <hi>Auguſtus</hi> did to his mutinous Army, <hi>[Audite me juvenes, quem juvenem ſenes Audierunt]</hi> Hear me Young men, whom ſometimes Old men have heard and obeyed: God forbid you ſhould be head-ſtrong ſons of <hi>Belial</hi> Yoakleſs, and ſo run headlong into the pit of deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: Be not like the wild aſſes colt, break not thro' Parents tears. Prayers, counſels and commands, to Hell: Alas! that any young perſons ſhould deſperat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contradict the perſwaſions of Miniſters, the motions of the Spirit, the checks of their own conſciences, the ſad warnings of their undone companions and the rods of God on their own backs,
<pb facs="tcp:108774:7"/> and haſte through all theſe to the pit, and never ſtop till they be ſwallowed up in that Infernal Lake that burns with Fire and Brimſtone: you will ſay what would you have us to do? I anſwer, Act as Rational Creatures, inure your ſelves to Solemn conſideration: Conſider that you are Creatures of an higher rank than Bruits, that you have Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal never dying Souls, that God made you to Glorify and injoy him: that he hath given you a rule to act by, in order to another ſtate in the other World, that Sin hath depraved your natures, hath diprived you of Gods Image, brought you under his curſe: that Chriſt came to redeem Sinners, that ſaving Faith doth intereſt Souls in Chriſt: that Faith is the gift of God: that in your Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm you were ingaged to forſake the World, Fleſh and Devil: Conſider your ſins ſince you were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, confeſs them to God: review and renew your Baptiſmal vow, actualy renounce all other claimers, and give up your Selves to the Lord, underſtandingly, Deliberately, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally and Perpetually: improve Jeſus Chriſt, as the way, the truth, and the Life: Eſpouſe his intereſt: joyn with Gods People: Obey all his commands Attend on him in all his Ordinances: Be ſure you be ſincere: Exerciſe every Grace: aim at Perfection: keep a conſtant watch over your hearts and ways: maintaining a dayly war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare againſt all Spiritual Enemies: prepare for death: and conſider where you muſt lodg when the King of Terrours lays its cold hand of Arreſt upon you: and make your Accounts ſtreight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that great reckoning day: and be ſure you put on Chriſt, and improve him as your Advocate, that he may Anſwer for you at that day.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:108774:8"/>
            <p>Theſe things I do but touch: for my great deſign is, the quicken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and incouraging of Parents on the behalf of their Poſterity: ſome whereof are left to themſelves by the Lord to go aſtray, which occaſioned <hi>Mr. Lawrence's excellent Treatiſe of Parents Groans;</hi> nor is it his caſe only, but many others alſo, ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular inſtances are freſh in memory, which have brought ſome Godly Parents gray hairs with Sorrow to their Graves: ſome well known Servants of God having never ſeen any hopeful ſymptoms of Grace upon ſome or all ther Children in their Life time, and had ſome ſad temptations to queſtion the truth of of God in his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: yet even in the very pangs of Death reacht to and claſpt hard this Bleſſed Word, dying in the hopes of its Efficacy for themſelves and theirs, and the ſubject being recommended to me, was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly treated on in a Funeral Diſcourſe, which upon requeſt, I was willing to tranſcribe, for the incouragement of Poor afflicted Parents, that are bowed down with heart-grief for their offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Children; I confeſs the ſubject is novel and ſingular, and ſuch as I have not ſeen any Treatiſe upon: and having walked in an untrodden path, I hope I may obtain a pardon from God and Man of ſome Erratick motion, whilſt the tendency is Gods Glory and the good of Souls.</p>
            <p>I hope none will reject this Treatiſe, becauſe it ſeems a limited Subject, as if they were not concerned in it, for as 'tis handled it is extenſive to all, Parents, Children; yea ſuch as have no Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, are dealt with in this ſmall Treatiſe, for their Inſtruction and Conſolation: ſuch as it is I commend to Believing, Praying Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, following it with my poor Prayers, that all the Children of the Covenant, may be Covenanted Souls, and that Parents may be comforted in the Grace of God in their Poſterity, and both may meet in Glory; and if any reap and receive any advantage, I have my reward, and do humbly beg the Inceſſant Prayers of all that can Pray</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>For The poor Servant of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> O. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:108774:8"/>
            <head>A General Scheme or view of the Chief Contents of this <hi>Treatiſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 1.</label> The Context cleared, the Text ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, <hi>10</hi> Doctrines briefly hinted <hi>Page 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Ch. 2.</label> The main Doctrin, Propounded, Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Explained, by ſome things premiſed <hi>9.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Ch. 3.</label> What this Covenant is, and who are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it. <hi>16.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Ch. 4.</label> Six grounds of hope which Parents have from the Covenant for their Children. <hi>24.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Ch. 5.</label> Six other grounds of Incouragement to Parents for their ſurviving Children. <hi>32.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Ch. 6.</label> An Anſwer to a great objection, in ſeven particular Conſiderations. <hi>39.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Ch. 7.</label> An uſe of Conviction to Irreligious Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and graceleſs Children. <hi>48.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Ch. 8.</label> An uſe of Exhortation to Children both of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncovenanted and Covenanted Parents, and to ſuch as have no Children. <hi>59.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Ch. 9.</label> Another branch of Exhortation to all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents that have Children, ten motives to do their utmost to leave them within the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: what means to be uſed. <hi>69.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Ch. 10.</label> The laſt mean to be uſed for Childrens good is Earneſt Prayer for them. Twelve ſeveral Pleas and Arguments helping Parents in Prayers. Some Caſes of Conſcience anſwered. <hi>79.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:108774:9"/>
            <head>Theſe Books Written and Publiſhed by Mr. <hi>Oliver Heywood;</hi> are to be ſold by <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>THE Sure Mercies of <hi>David;</hi> being the fruits of ſome Meditations from <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3.</item>
               <item>Chriſt diſplayed as the choiceſt gift and beſt Maſter: from <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. And <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.13. Written by Mr. <hi>Nath. Heywood,</hi> and publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Mr. <hi>Oliver Heywood.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iſraels</hi> Lamentation after the Lord: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome Meditations upon 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.2.</item>
               <item>The Holy Life and Happy Death of Mr. <hi>John Angier.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cloſet Prayer: Or a Chriſtians Duty, from <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.6.</item>
               <item>Baptiſmal Bonds renewed: On <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.5.</item>
               <item>Meetneſs for Heaven upon <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.12. deſigned for a Funeral Legacy.</item>
               <item>Advice to an only Child, or excellent Counſel to all Young Perſons, containing the Sum and Subſtance of Experimental and Practical Divinity. Written by an Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and Judicious Divine for the Private uſe of an only Child now made publick for the Benefit of all. Publiſhed by Mr. <hi>Oliver Heywood.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:108774:9"/>
            <head>Dying Parent's Living Hopes for their ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving Children, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Sam. 23.5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Although my houſe be not ſo with God, yet he hath made with me an Everlaſting Covenant, ordered in all things and ſure: for this is all my Salvation, and all my Deſire, although he make it not to grow.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The Context cleared, the Text explained, Doctrines raiſed.</head>
               <p>THeſe words contain dying <hi>Davids</hi> living comfort: the Covenant was the only Cordial to his fainting Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; when the World lookt black about him, here's light ariſeth out of obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: juſt as it was with <hi>Oecolampadius</hi> dying, and clapping his hand on his Breaſt, cried <hi>[hic ſat lucis]</hi> here's light enough: ſo <hi>David</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:108774:10"/> and a Believing Soul, looking above ſees all good in the Covenant; looking within, ſees the countervain of it, ſaith, here, here alone is light:<note place="margin">Job 29.3.</note> by his light I walk through darkneſs. This ſhall be my [<hi>vade mecum,</hi> or] compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion through this Pilgrimage of the World, and this only ſhall be my [<hi>viand</hi> and <hi>viaticum</hi>] ſupport and ſupply when I paſs through the Valley of the Shadow of Death. Farewel empty, filthy World, welcome the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate preſence of my Covenanted God. I am going from a Priſon to a Pallace, from ſorrow to ſolace, from Sin to ſweet In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of God: and the only foundation of my hopes is this Goſpel Covenant: A ſad, and ſorry dying Miſer, ready to breath out his ſenſual, ſenſeleſs Soul, got a <hi>Jacobus</hi> piece of Gold, clapt it to his Breaſt, ſaying, Some wiſer than others, but I will dye with this Cordial at my Heart: but at laſt pluckt it away ſaying, it will not do, alas it will not do; Gold it ſelf is no Cordial, it cannot diſarm death nor arm againſt it, it hath loſt its vertue: nothing but Gods Covenant will ſtand in ſtead: the dying Child of God is like a Standard bearer, who when the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel is loſt, wraps himſelf in his Colours and therein is ſafe, marching triumphantly through Armies of Enemies, untoucht into his Fathers Pallace. Oh happy Soul that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys and improves this Covenant!</p>
               <p>The Context tells us, that theſe be the laſt words of <hi>David,</hi> not abſolutely as though he breathed his laſt, after he had uttered
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:108774:10"/> them (for there are ſeveral expreſſions and tranſactions after) but comparatively, they were uttered towards the latter end of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s Life. Now the dying words of Pious men are gracious, ſerious, ponderous: they uſe not to ſpend their breath about trifles.</p>
               <p>In the Context, we have 1. The Porch, or Introduction. 2. The Temple, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the Goſpel Covenant.</p>
               <p>In the Porch or Introduction we have theſe two things. 1. The Penman, inſtrument, or Amanuenſis, who ſpoke theſe words, <hi>David.</hi> 2. The Authour who dictated them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Penman, or Inſtrument, <hi>David,</hi> is deſcribed theſe four ways.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. By his natural deſcent, the Son of <hi>Jeſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. By his Royal Dignity, raiſed up on high.</item>
                  <item>3. By his Divine Unction, anointed of God.</item>
                  <item>4. By his Employment, Exerciſe, ſweet-Pſalmiſt of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> whoſe breath is ſweet to this Day.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="2">2. The Authour that dictated to <hi>David.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <head>Viz.</head>
                     <item>1. The Holy Ghoſt, Spirit ſpake by me.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Viz.</hi> 2. God the Father, the God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Viz.</hi> 3. Jeſus Chriſt the Mediator of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, called here the Rock of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> as he is called, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. In the Temple or the Matter <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks are alſo two things conſiderable.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The nature of <hi>David</hi>'s Regiment.</item>
                  <item>2. The Excellency of the Covenant.</item>
               </list>
               <p>For the former which unfolds to us, the nature and properties of <hi>David</hi>'s Kingdom,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:108774:11"/> as the type, and of Chriſts as the Antitype, in four particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The holineſs of it, he that ruleth over men muſt be juſt, ruling in the fear of God; a brave character.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The happineſs of it, he ſhall be as the light of the morning, when the Sun riſeth, a morning without clouds.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The fruitneſs of it, as the tender graſs ſpringing out of the Earth, by clear ſhining after Rain.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Here's an uncomfortable exception with reference to <hi>David</hi>'s Family and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, in theſe words <hi>[Although my houſe be not ſo with God.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Here's an Excellent deſcription of the nature, properties, and ſuitableneſs of the Goſpel-Covenant, in theſe four particulars.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Viz.</head>
                  <item>1. The dureableneſs of it, Everlaſting.</item>
                  <item>2. The orderlineſs of it, Ordered.</item>
                  <item>3. The ſureneſs, certainty of it.</item>
                  <item>4. The ſuitableneſs to <hi>David,</hi> as to his.
<list>
                        <item>1. Preſent deſires in this World.</item>
                        <item>2. Eternal Salvation hereafter.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>You ſee the Text is a full ſtore houſe, a rich treaſury, a bleſſed Magazine, whence we may fetch both meat and medicine, food and phyſick, work and reward, all things that concern grace and glory.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Text then preſents to us <hi>David</hi>'s caſe, and 2. Cure. 1. His Caſe is preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed negatively, <hi>[Although my houſe be not ſo with God.]</hi> 2. His Cure poſitively, which is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108774:11"/>
[the Covenant,] that's a Salve for all Sores, a Remedy for all Maladies, a Supply for all Wants.</p>
               <p>I am not ignorant that ſome carry the ſenſe thus, <hi>Although my houſe be not ſo with God,</hi> i. e. my houſe is not ſuch an unſtable, inconſtant thing, to alter and change as the Weather, from a glorious Sun-ſhine morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to a dark cloudy, gloomy evening, ſo it may prove, a ſtormy, rainy day; no, no, my Houſe and Family is fixed, ſetled, ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did, and compleat, if not in my outward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs at preſent, yet in the Meſſiah to come out of my Loynes in the fulneſs of time: his Kingdom will appear, and ſhine moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and break in pieces all other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and it ſhall ſtand for ever; ſo you read, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44.</p>
               <p>But (though that be a great truth) I am apt to incline to thoſe Interpreters, that take this as a conceſſion, concerning the defects and imperfection of Piety and Tranquillity in <hi>David</hi>'s Family, <hi>q. d.</hi> I muſt needs confeſs, that neither I nor my Children have lived ſo exactly, or ruled ſo uprightly in the fear of God as we ought; we have had our faults and folly, which have clouded our Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Reputation, and therefore have not injoyed ſuch uninterrupted proſperity as we might, had we walked more cloſely and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly, and therefore ſad Clouds and Storms have darkened and diſturbed our Heaven, yea oft benighted our ſtate, domeſtical po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical, eccleſiaſtical, as well as perſonal, my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108774:12"/> Children have not been like tender Graſs, ſpringing up to maturity, but ſome of them cut off in the prime of their days; I have been baniſht from my Throne, and family, not ſuffered to build God an Houſe, nor abide in his Sanctuary, my wounded Spirit hath ſighed out many heavy groans, God hath oft with-drawn his Grace, hid his Face, and left my Soul on the brink of helliſh deſpair; yet for all this I can in my loweſt ebbs caſt my Eye upon the Goſpel-Covenant, and fetch relief from that in my loweſt ſtate, inward or outward.</p>
               <p>Many Doctrines may be drawn out of this large, and full Text.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Doctrine 1.</hi> That it's a ſingular mercy to be be truſted with a Family.</q>
               <p>This is implied, and owned by <hi>David,</hi> in 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17.16, 25. God ſetteth the ſolitary in Families, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.6.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Doct. 2.</hi> Houſe-holders muſt make inſpection into their Families.</q>
               <p>So doth <hi>David</hi> here, and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.2, 3. he had a large Family, State-affairs on his hands, yet prays with his Family, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.20. puts it not off to Stewards or Chaplains. See <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.23.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Doct. 3.</hi> A Religious Family is to be with God.</q>
               <p>Although my Houſe be not ſo with God, he earneſtly deſires all the members of his Family might be with God, laments the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, for the Lord is with them that are with him, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.2.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:108774:12"/>
                  <hi>Doct. 4.</hi> The beſt Families have their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and imperfections.</q>
               <p>
                  <hi>David</hi>'s Family (for all his care) may be far from the rule, not only as to individual members, but as to the complex body of a Family; there were diſorders even in Chriſts own Family.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Doct. 5.</hi> Family-faults bring family plagues, family-defects produce family-afflictions.</q>
               <p>God will not ſpare ſinning families, though dear to him, nay they ſhall ſmart ſooneſt and ſoreſt, Amos 3.2. <hi>You only have I known of all the families of the Earth, therefore I will puniſh you.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Doct. 6.</hi> Family-miſcarriages do greatly trouble gracious houſe-holders.</q>
               <p>He ſpeaks of it, with ſad reſentment. Oh what bitterneſs is it to a godly Father, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, to find diſorders in ſuch as are under his charge!</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Doct. 7.</hi> The Covenant of Grace is extenſive and comprehenſive.</q>
               <p>The godly have much comfort and content in it, with reference not only to themſelves, but their houſes and families.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Doct. 8.</hi> The Covenant of Grace is Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</q>
               <p>It is from all Eternity in the Covenant of Redemption, betwixt Father and Son, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1, 2. and endures for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.9.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Doct. 9.</hi> There is a comely and admirable order in the Goſpel-Covenant.</q>
               <p>An order of perſons, in the Fathers Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Sons Redemption, Holy Ghoſts Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:108774:13"/> believers reception: An order of things ſupream, ſubordinate cauſes, means, inſtruments, promiſes, priviledges, principles, and practices; all keep their places, they do not interfere or thwart each other.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Doct. 10.</hi> The Goſpel-covenant is ſure and ſtable.</q>
               <p>Things are not left at uncertainties, nor depend on the mutable Will of Man, as of old it was with <hi>Adam:</hi> but they are the ſure Mercies of <hi>David, Iſa.</hi> 55.2. and 54.9, 10.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Doct. 11.</hi> There's that in the Covenat that anſwers a Chriſtian's deſires.</q>
               <p>As the Chriſtians deſire is mainly carried to it; ſo there is that in it which anſwers and ſatisfies thoſe deſires: deſires are vaſt and immenſe, but the contents of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant run parallel, and are every way adequate to juſt deſires.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Doct. 12.</hi> A Chriſtians Salvation is wrapt up in the Goſpel covenant.</q>
               <p>Upon this may a Child of God venture his Soul. Eternal Life is contained and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in it.</p>
               <p>I wave all theſe, and ſhall conſider the Text in a two fold notion, or relation.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. In a domeſtical ſenſe.</item>
                  <item>2. In a perſonal reſpect.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The former refers to <hi>David</hi>'s Houſe, the latter to his Heart and Soul: this bleſſed Covenant was <hi>David</hi>'s chief relief, in both theſe caſes: from the former obſerve,</p>
               <p>That notwithſtanding the ſins and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in a godly mans family which occaſion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:108774:13"/> much grief to his Spirit, yet he is ſupported and ſatisfied with Gods gracious Goſpel co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</p>
               <p>From the latter acceptation obſerve this.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> That Covenant Relation is the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a dying Christians ſafety, ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſalvation.</q>
               <p>It is the former Doctrine I ſhall ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to at preſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The Doctrine cleared from the Text, ſome things premiſed.</head>
               <p>THE principal point I propoſe from the Text concerns <hi>David</hi>'s family, for 1. He mentions his houſe in the beginning of the Text. 2. The latter end of the verſe refers to his houſe, [Although he make it (<hi>i. e.</hi> my houſe) not to grow] <hi>i. e.</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in number, power, honour.</p>
               <p>The former part of the verſe is variouſly rendred, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>nec tanta est domus mea apud Deum.</hi> Nor is my houſe ſo great, or of ſo much worth with God. Alaſs what is my houſe at beſt, my pedigree is mean and baſe. <hi>David</hi> diſdains not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on his deſpicable original, though ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to the culminating point of civil and ſpiritual promotion, as a King and Prophet: he magnifieth God, and villifieth, yea nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth himſelf, 2 Sam. 7.18. <hi>Who am I, O
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108774:14"/> Lord God, and what is my houſe that thou haſt brought me hitherto?</hi> others thus, <hi>plus eſt quam haec domus mea ante Deum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chaldee.</note> Jon. <hi>i. e.</hi> there is more in the Covenant than this my houſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God. All the Families in the World amount not to ſo much as one Meſſias, he, he only is the noble flouriſhing branch ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of my Family, that's worth us all, who conveys life and ſap to us all,<note place="margin">Iſa. 11.1.</note> this is the Rod out of the Stem of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> and a branch growing out of its Roots, and they ſhall hang on him all the glory of his Fathers houſe:<note place="margin">Iſa. 22.24.</note> my whole family would fall to ruine but for him, on whoſe behalf it muſt be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, that he may be born of it: yea who only upholds it.</p>
               <p>Others thus, <hi>[quamvis not ſit it a] i. e.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, my Family, and Kingdom be not ſo holy, as to perform the conditions of the Covenant ſo exactly as God requireth, we are guilty in many reſpects before God, and he hath whipt us ſore, yet Gods Covenant is the ground of my hope for my Family, and I doubt not but my Lord will make it good.</p>
               <p>And what <hi>David</hi> ſaith of his Family, any Child of God may ſay of his, except in the peculiar caſe of the Meſſiah ſpringing out of his loins. Thence we may ſafely draw this</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> That notwithstanding the ſins and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings in a godly mans Family, which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion much grief to his Spirit, yet he is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported and ſatisfied with Gods gracious Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel covenant.</q>
               <p>In handling this point I ſhall
<list>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:108774:14"/>
                     <item>1. Premiſe ſome things fit to be known.</item>
                     <item>2. Give the proof of the point.</item>
                     <item>3. Anſwer a main objection.</item>
                     <item>4. Make a ſhort Application.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The things to be premiſed are four,
<list>
                     <item>1. What may befal a Godly mans family.</item>
                     <item>2. Why are theſe a grief to his Spirit.</item>
                     <item>3. What is the Covenant that ſupports him.</item>
                     <item>4. What is in the Covenant to bear him up.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>A word of all theſe briefly.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What may fall out in a godly mans fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily that may occaſion his grief?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſhall reduce theſe to two heads.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Corruptions breaking out.</item>
                  <item>2. Afflictions breaking in on his houſe, ſin and ſuffering, and indeed ſuffering is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per fruit of ſinning.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. Corruption may break out in godly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies: I ſhall not need to inſtance in <hi>Adams, Noahs, Abrahams, Iſaacs,</hi> yea even in <hi>Jacobs, Aarons, Samuels,</hi> &amp;c. I ſhall keep to <hi>David</hi>'s, Alas, corruption brake out ſadly. 1. In himſelf. 2. In his Children. 1. <hi>David</hi> was guilty of, 1. Sins of Ommiſſion, poſſibly not inſtructing, reſtraining, or not puniſhing <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Abſolom,</hi> and not croſſing <hi>Adonijah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Kin. 13.21.</note> 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 1.6. <hi>David</hi> was too indulgent for which he ſmarted. Yea, 2. He was guilty of foul ſins of commiſſion: as Adultery, and Murder of his faithful Servant <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.4, 27. raſhneſs towards <hi>Mephiboſheth,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.29. ſometimes lying, changing his behaviour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. His Children alſo were deeply guilty, <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:108774:15"/> Inceſt,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 13.23, 28. 2 Sam. 15.1. 1 Kin. 1.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Abſolom</hi>'s Rebellion, and <hi>Adoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jahs</hi> Ambition. Alas that there ſhould be found ſuch groſs abominations in godly <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s Family! yet this was not his caſe only, it's ſaid of <hi>Samuel,</hi> that his ſons walked not in his ways, but turned aſide after lucre, and took bribes and perverted judgment, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And what a flood gate of troubles did theſe ſins open, which guſhed in upon him, deep called to deep,<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.7.</note> all Gods Waves and Billows went over him, Remember <hi>David</hi> and all his Afflictions,<note place="margin">Pſal. 132.1.</note> ſaith he, how nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, how ponderous! ſome of his deſireable Children dying in the height of their career, by the eminent hand of juſtice one died in infancy to puniſh his iniquity:<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.14.</note> beſides for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Enemies, he had a doomy morning, noon, evening, what bloody Wars with <hi>Saul,</hi> and his houſe, with Philiſtines, Ammonites! what ſad Tragedies, Inſurrections, Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Confuſions, threatning a total Diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation and extirpation, ſo that <hi>David</hi> might call ſome Child <hi>Beriah,</hi> as <hi>Ephraim</hi> did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it went evil with his houſe. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7. 21, 22, 23. and ſo it hath done with many a good mans houſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Why are theſe breakings out of ſin, and breakings in of ſufferings in their Families, ſuch a grief to godly houſeholders?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> For the firſt, it muſt needs trouble them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe by ſin God is greatly diſpleaſed, his name much diſhonoured, Religion diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited, the hearts of the Godly ſadened, the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:108774:15"/> wicked ſcandalized, hardened; Motes in Profeſſors are beams, Mountains in the eyes of Prophane; what will they ſay? they are no better than we, what are they but a pack of hypocrites, to what purpoſe is all their whining and praying? Our Children carry as civilly as theirs, where's the Covenant they boaſt of? Hence <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 42.3. <hi>My tears have been my meat day and night, while they continually ſay unto me, where is thy God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. They are greatly afflicted with the ſins of Children, becauſe the beloved of their Souls are endanger'd, they are pieces of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as their own Souls, how can I endure to ſee my own fleſh ſcorched, and tormented in Hell-flames? Oh! that Child that came out of my Loins, my Bowels, to be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from God, a companion with Devils, a Fire-brand in Hell, the mention of it ſinks my Spirits? Is all my labour loſt? their Souls loſt? oh who can endure to think of it? no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if that be the firſt of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Proverbs,<note place="margin">Prov. 15.28.</note> 
                  <hi>ch.</hi> 1. <hi>A wiſe Son maketh a glad Father; but a fooliſh Son is the heavineſs of his Mother.</hi> Yea,<note place="margin">17. 25</note> he frequently repeats it: other afflictions lye on the back, this goes to the heart, ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.1, 2, 3.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſciouſneſs in Parents of their own guilt, makes Childrens Miſcarriages, more uneaſie and afflictive. O I read my ſin in my Childs folly, alas, omiſſion of due in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, admonition, correction hath brought my Child to this, I may thank my ſelf, I
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:108774:16"/> have taught the young ones by my bad Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, I have not watcht over them, pray'd for them, been ſo jealous of them, to offer Sacrifice for them continually, as I find <hi>Job</hi> did, <hi>chap.</hi> 1. 5, 3, 25. who can tell, but if I had been faithful, I might have prevented all this? Oh, my Childs ſin brings my youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful vanities to my remembrance, thus I dealt with my Father, to this pitch I arrived. God puniſheth my ſin with my Childs: I am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily guilty, this cuts deep, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.18.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The affliction is heavier becauſe it doth in ſome ſort weaken Parents confidence in the Covenant, and endanger their faith in the Promiſe. Godly Parents are ready to ſay when a Child is born and baptized as <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> of <hi>Eliab,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 16.6.</note> ſurely the Lords anointed is before him, this is a lovely child, I hope this may honour God in his day, but the child grows up, and degenerates, anſwers, not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations, but grows debaucht, and hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; old in ſin, though young in years, and now the Godly Parents hopes are daſht and daunted, he is put to a ſtand, and knows not what to think or ſay, but concludes ſadly, with the two diſciples in another caſe, we truſted that it had been he (this Child)<note place="margin">Luk. 24.21.</note> that ſhould have been an honour to God, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to me, and a good inſtrument in the Church, but oh how am I diſappointed! he proves the greateſt affliction I have oh what's become of the Covenant? have I not ſome reaſon to queſtion either Gods faithfulneſs or mine own intereſt? This was the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:108774:16"/> of holy <hi>David,</hi> with whom the Covenant was made expreſly and immediately, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.20. yea God gives him all the aſſurances imaginable his word, his oath, <hi>ver.</hi> 34, 35. yet <hi>ver.</hi> 49. he ſaith Lord, where are thy former loving kindneſſes, which thou ſwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt unto <hi>David</hi> in thy truth? A ſad expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, as if God kept not touch with <hi>David,</hi> why what's the matter? the reaſon was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Providences run counter to Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: croſſes ſeemed to make void Gods Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>ver.</hi> 38. to 46. but thou haſt caſt off and abhorred, thou haſt been wroth with thine anointed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alas, <hi>David,</hi> where's thy Faith? But ſo it is that ſenſe prevails in the beſt Saints above Faith at ſome ſeaſons: but moſt of all in this caſe, when the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Covenant, croſs the Ends of the Covenant? and no doubt this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a great grief of heart to a godly Soul; when he is thus ſadly non pluſt, till the light of the Covenant rightly underſtood unriddle this myſtery, the poor Chriſtian is in great perplexity: <hi>David</hi> had a promiſe by <hi>Samuel</hi> that he ſhould be King, yet ſaith in his heart,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 27.1.</note> I ſhall now periſh one day by the hand of <hi>Saul.</hi> Why ſo? why, his preſent danger ſeemed to ſuperſede the performance of that promiſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 116.11.</note> and though he ſaid in his haſte all men are liars, yet when he came to himſelf, certainly he would fret and vex himſelf, that he ſhould ſo wrong himſelf, and <hi>Samuel</hi> yea and caſt ſuch an unworthy reflection upon God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as though, he were unfaithful to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108774:17"/> thus will the Godly Soul do at laſt, but at preſent he is upon a ſtrange rack, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured betwixt hope and fear.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> What this Covenant is, and what is in it to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Chriſtian.</head>
               <p>IT would be ſuperfluous to ſay much of the nature of a Covenant, yet take this ſhort deſcription of it.</p>
               <p>A Covenant is a voluntary mutual com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact between two parties, containing bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits to be injoyed, and duties to be performed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It's a compact between two parties, for though a ſingle perſon may make a promiſe, yet a covenant is betwixt two or more, and of parties formerly at diſtance; this is the caſe betwixt God and Man, ſo <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.28.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It's a mutual reciprocal compact, both parties muſt be ingaged, therefore it's called the Bond of the Covenant, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.87. becauſe though they were free before yet now they are become bond.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It's a voluntary compact, both parties were free before they were obliged by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, covenanting is an Elective act, God is a free Agent: nothing but pure love in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced him to covenant with Man, <hi>Deut.</hi> 77, 8. and though man was not abſolutely free, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods Creature, and ſo bound to his Creator, yet his actual entring into Covenant
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:108774:17"/> is a voluntary act, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.3. <hi>Thy People ſhall be willing</hi> [or Volunteers] <hi>in the day of thy Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Betwixt Covenanters there is mutual obligation to conferring of benefits, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming of duties [called the <hi>habenda</hi> and the <hi>agenda</hi>] things to be conferred by God, and received by man, and duties on mans part if he expect any benefits from God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.19. If you be willing and obedient, you ſhall eat the good of the Land.</p>
               <p>Yet in the Covenant of Grace betwixt God and Man, there are two things peculiar.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That there is an interpoſing Mediator, our bleſſed Jeſus, the days-man that lays his hand upon both: now ſaith the Apoſtle, a mediator, is not of one, but God is one,<note place="margin">Job 9.55.</note> 
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.20. <hi>i. e.</hi> his buſineſs is to reconcile parties not only diſtinct, but different.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This Mediator is alſo ſurety or ſponſor, to be a ſuſceptor or undertaker for both parties, <hi>i. e.</hi> to perform what is neceſſary, both what concerns conferring of benefits on Gods part, not formally, and perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conditions on mans part, as though Chriſt believes and repents for us, to ſave us a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of repenting or believing, but merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, purchaſing theſe Graces for us, and efficiently working them in us, thus Jeſus is made a ſurety of a better Teſtament, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.22 on Gods part, he brings in everlaſting righteouſneſs, and makes God friends with us, and all his attributes amicable to us, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd for us: on our part working gracious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions and actings, which are the conditions
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:108774:18"/> of the Covenant, ſo the whole lyes upon Chriſt:<note place="margin">Col. 3.11.</note> and <hi>he is all in all:</hi> he is reſponſible for God and Man, being only able and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as God and Man, to fulfill neceſſary terms on both parts: thus God promiſeth what he requires, and gives what he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, Jer. 3.19. <hi>But I ſaid, how ſhall I put thee among the Children, and give thee a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant land, a goodly heritage of the Hoſt of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? And I ſaid thou ſhalt call me my Father, and ſhalt not turn away from me. [Thou ſhalt]</hi> there's Gods undertaking, to give filial diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and perſeverance: Oh infinite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance of Divine Wiſdom and Free grace!</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Directory.</note> An Eminent Divine obſerves, that 1. The Goſpel relating matters of fact, is an hiſtory. 2. Declaring terms on which God will be ſerved, is a law of Grace. 3. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering promiſes of Life conditionally, it is Gods Covenant. 4. As accepted by Man, it is a mutual Covenant betwixt God and Man: this Law and Covenant of Grace, which was purchaſed by Chriſts Death, is that legacy he left to the World, diſpenſed by his Ambaſſadours, and effectually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to the Legatees, or Heirs of Promiſe, by his grand Executor the Holy Ghoſt. This then is the great ſecurity of mans Salvation, <hi>That God worketh in us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 2.13. 1 Pet. 1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>both to will and to do,</hi> that <hi>we are kept by the mighty power of God through Faith unto Salvation.</hi> This is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the Goſpel diſpenſation of the New-Covenant, the Old-Covenant laid all the ſtreſs on the ſhoulders of mutable man,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:108774:18"/> and therefore it is judged, that the Covenant of God made with <hi>Adam</hi> in innocency, was peculiar to him in that eſtate and went no farther, is not at all continued in any force ſince the Fall, for <hi>if there had been a law gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which could have given life, then righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs had been by the Law,</hi> Gal. 3.21. but it is by the Goſpel-Covenant that we are juſtified and ſaved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What's all this to the purpoſe? All this ſeems to be perſonal not relating to poſterity, but you told us of grounds of hope for Children from the Covenant: how come Children concerned in this Covenant?</p>
               <p>This leads me to the</p>
               <p n="4">4th Thing premiſed, <hi>viz.</hi> What is there in the Goſpel-covenant, that is ground of ſupport to Parents on the behalf of their Children?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, in general, Parents and Children are legally one party, and in civil contracts are uſually involved in the ſame bottom, ſo in the firſt Covenant <hi>Adam</hi> being a publick perſon, repreſented all his Poſterity, for <hi>judgment was by one to condemnation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5.16, 18.</note> yea <hi>upon all men:</hi> we ſmart for <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin. And in the Old Teſtament-diſpenſation of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, Gen. 17.7. <hi>I will eſtabliſh my Covenant between Me and Thee, and thy Seed after thee in their Generations.</hi> And afterwards in <hi>Moſes</hi> days, when God renewed the Covenant, he ſaith Deut. 29.14, 15. <hi>Neither with you only do I make this Covenant, and this Oath, with him that ſtandeth here with us this
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:108774:19"/> before the Lord our God, and alſo with him that is not here with us this day, i. e.</hi> With their Poſterity, and ſo the People did underſtand it, Deut. 5.3. <hi>The Lord made not</hi> (i. e. on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) <hi>this Covenant with our Fathers, but with us, even us who are all of us here alive this day.</hi> And in the New Teſtament, the Apoſtle ſaith, Act. 2.39. <hi>For the promiſe is unto you, and to your Children:</hi> this is a <hi>[faedus ad ſucceſſores tranſiens]</hi> a Covenant that paſſeth to ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors. Bargains, Leaſes, Legacies may paſs to Children, yea Children may ſuffer for their Parents faults, Traitors Sons loſe their Fathers inheritance.</p>
               <p>Now we muſt look upon Children under a double capacity. 1. Children of Heathens, or Jews; Turks, or Infidels. 2. Children of Chriſtian Parents: concerning the former we have little to ſay. 'Tis the latter we treat of, and of theſe alſo, 1. Some are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by an external profeſſion in Covenant. 2. Others are ſincerely, ſavingly in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God: we can ſay little concerning the former, we inſiſt chiefly on the latter: and of both or all theſe, 1. Some Children dye, in Infancy, 2. Others live to years of maturity: I ſhall hint a word or two of the former, though it be the latter that I princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally deſign.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For Children dying in Infancy, if we had any Scripture diſcovery concerning the Election of all Infants, or that Chriſt had expiated the guilt of ſuch Infants, or that effectual ſaving Grace doth always attend the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:108774:19"/> Ordinance of Baptiſm, though they be brought under it (which yet many are not) the queſtion were quickly determined, but what God doth with the Souls of ſuch Infants, we have not ſufficient means to underſtand, and therefore leave them to Gods good pleaſure. But concerning the Seed of thoſe that truly fear God, of one or both the Parents, we have ground of hope for their Salvation: for</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are Holy, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. and though it be faederally or relatively holy yet may be really, and ſo be ſaved.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Our Saviour ſaith,<note place="margin">Mark 10.14.</note> of ſuch is <hi>the Kingdom of God,</hi> or <hi>of Heaven,</hi> Mat. 19.14. not only ſuch as have the diſpoſition of Children, but In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants themſelves, may be Church-members here, and glorify'd hereafter.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Children of Godly Parents are in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God, <hi>Now to</hi> Abraham <hi>and to his Seed were the promiſes made,</hi> Gal. 3.16. natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral as well as ſpiritual: it's true there was a Covenant of peculiarity to give his Seed the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and it's as true, the text ſpeaks not of <hi>Seeds</hi> but <hi>one Seed,</hi> that is Chriſt, but the Scripture affirms, <hi>that in his Seed,</hi> Chriſt, yea <hi>in thee,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>ſhall all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of the Earth be bleſſed,</hi> Gen. 12.3. for ſo doth the Apoſtle interpret, and apply it, Act. 3.25. <hi>Ye are the Children of the Prophets and of the Covenant, which God hath made with our Fathers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>David</hi> had good hopes that his Child was gone to Heaven, 2 Sam. 12.25. <hi>I ſhall go to him, but he ſhall not return to me.</hi> Obſ.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:108774:20"/> 1. He doth not only mean into the ſtate of the dead, where the child is, but into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven where <hi>I ſhall find him,</hi> for his Carcaſs was but part of him, and the leaſt part. 2. This hope he had of him, though the Child was begot in Adultery. 3. Though the Child was ſtruck with death, as a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>David</hi>'s ſin. 4. Though the Child had not yet circumciſion the Seal of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, for <hi>he died on the ſeventh day,</hi> ver. 18. and we know that Circumciſion was not to be till the eighth day.<note place="margin">Gen. 17.12.</note> So that it ſeems the ſtreſs is not laid on the Seal, but on the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant: ſo that we ſee grounds of hope for the Eternal Salvation of the Infants, of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Parents. But how and whence this comes to paſs, that ſuch Infants become ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Eternal Salvation, that's a great Queſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> thinks that Infants have actual Faith, from Mat. 18.6. <hi>Whoſo ſhall offend one of theſe little ones which believe in me.</hi> So reaſon is in Infants <hi>[tanquam in principio &amp; Radice]</hi> in its principle, root, habit, virtually though not yet actually produced.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Others ſay they are ſaved by ſome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar, unknown, unſpeakable way without Faith, but the text ſaith, Mark 16.16. <hi>He that believeth and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved, but he that believeth not ſhall be damned:</hi> how far this extends with reference to Infants I know not.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Others ſay that Parents Faith is alſo Childrens, according to the Tenour of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:108774:20"/> Covenant; <hi>[I will be thy God and the God of thy Seed]</hi> thus Children have faith after a ſort. So the text ſaith, Rom. 11.16. <hi>If the Root be holy, the Branches are alſo holy.</hi> So in humane Laws the Father and the Heir are but one Perſon: of this opinion is Mr. <hi>Perkin</hi>'s, and produceth the teſtimony of the Antients, as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> and <hi>Bernard,</hi> ſaying it is meet, and for the honour of God, that to whom age denies their own Faith, Grace ſhould grant to them, a benefit by the Faith of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Perk vol.</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 486. where he anſwers <hi>Bellarmine</hi>'s objection, <q>That by this means Children ſhall be born Believers, and ſo be conceived and born without original ſin.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
                  <q>Believing Parents ſuſtain two perſons, one whereby they are men, and thus they bring forth Children, having Mans Nature with all the corruptions of nature: the other as they are holy men, and Believers, and thus they bring forth Infants, that are not ſo much their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as the Children of God; and Infants are Gods Children, not by vertue of their birth, but by means of Parents Faith, which intitles them to all the bleſſings of the Covenant. Thus he.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But this is not the ſubject of our preſent deſign, and conſideration.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:108774:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> What grounds of hope Parents have from the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant for their Adult, and ſurviving Children.</head>
               <p>THE ſecond head in the proſecuting of this Doctrine is the proof of the point, That notwithſtanding the ſins and ſufferings, breaking forth in a godly man's Family, or breaking in upon it, which occaſion much grief to his Spirit, yet he is, and hath reaſon to be ſupported and ſatisfied from Gods gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Goſpel-covenant.</p>
               <p>I am very ſenſible I have undertaken a difficult province, and walk in an untrodden path; But this I may confidently affirm, that whatever befalls a covenanted Soul, he may fetch all good out of this bleſſed trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury: for 1. Either his Children ſhall be laid hold on by converting Grace; or 2. They ſhall not: if they be, oh what cauſe will he have to magnifie Covenant-love, on their behalf? if not, ſtill he will exceedingly adore Covenant-grace, on his own behalf, that hath made him to differ, and in the worſt caſe will find ſomething in the Covenant for ſupporting his Spirit, and ſanctifying his bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cup of Affliction, in the death of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. As to this latter, I ſhall ſay nothing, but refer you to a ſmall Treatiſe of Mr. <hi>John Flavel</hi>'s, called the Balm of the Covenant applied to the bleeding wounds of afflicted Saints, from this text.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:108774:21"/>
               <p>But my preſent buſineſs is to gather up ſuch gracious promiſes, as a Noſegay, or Poſie, out of the Garden of Scripture, as may refreſh the drooping hearts of Gods poor Children, ſorrowing for the miſcarriages of their Children, that they may turn them into Prayer, or uſe them as a Cordial to ſupport them, till the Lord ſhine upon the Souls of their beloved off-ſpring.</p>
               <p>In general obſerve that as the Covenant of Grace is a bleſſed conſtellation. So every promiſe is an orient refulgent Star, to give both light and influence to the weary Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller, in this dark and diſmal diſpenſation; wherein he is appalled through ſad fears that his Child ſhall be a caſt-away.</p>
               <p>The Queſtion is, what grounds of hope from Scripture have godly Parents, for their Children that are grown, or growing up and likely to ſurvive or out-live them? The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving of this is of exceeding great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and having ſearched the Sacred Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, I do find twelve ſorts of Promiſes that may incourage Parents Hearts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt and chief is God himſelf, Gen. 17.7. <hi>For I will eſtabliſh my Covenant between me and thee, and thy ſeed after thee, in their Generations for an Everlaſting Covenant: to be a God unto thee, and to thy ſeed after thee.</hi> This extends both to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Seed, and afterwards to his Spiritual Seed, all Gentile-believers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.12, 18. Oh what a privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is this! whatever God is, hath, or can be or do, is for believers, of all that's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:108774:22"/> divine power, wiſdom, goodneſs, mercy, holineſs, juſtice is the portion of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, and their Seed, whatever they can ask or expect in a God, ſhall be in due ſeaſon, laid out, in them, and for them: this one word is the ſubſtance and confluence of all good, ſpiritual, temporal, eternal, <hi>[Deus meus &amp; omnia]</hi> My God, is the moſt extenſive and comprehenſive word in the World: what can a man deſire more, and no leſs will give a gracious Soul content for himſelf and his Seed: no leſs is in the Covenant, Jer. 31.33. <hi>Bleſſed is the Nation whoſe God is the Lord.</hi> Pſal. 33.12. God (in ſome ſenſe) may be the God of Nations, Families, as well as Perſons: and if ſome boaſt of Pedigree, Wealth, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, numerous Poſterity, Worldly Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet let <hi>David</hi> reckon up the Epitome, the <hi>ſumma totalis</hi> of mans felicity, he will thus conclude, <hi>happy is that People whoſe God is the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 144.12, 15. Happy Parents that bequeath ſuch a Legacy to their Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, though they leave them in Poverty!</p>
               <p n="2">2. Next to that, and a mean to injoy God is Jeſus Chriſt the Mediator of the Covenant, Iſa. 42.6. <hi>I will give thee for a Covenant of the People, for a light of the Gentiles:</hi> it's true God vouchſafed to the Jewiſh Nation this privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.5.</note> that <hi>of them as concerning the Fleſh Chriſt came,</hi> but they cannot monopolize this glorious gift,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.13.</note> for now in Chriſt Jeſus <hi>we who ſometimes were afar off are made nigh by the blood of Chriſt,</hi> and poor Gentiles laying hold on the Covenant, are become free Denizons
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:108774:22"/> of all Jewiſh priviledges that are eſſential to Salvation,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.28.</note> for we <hi>are all one in Chriſt Jeſus</hi> and promiſes are <hi>to us that are afar off, even as many as the Lord our God ſhall</hi> call, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.39. even Chriſt himſelf, <hi>in whom all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God are yea, and in him,</hi> Amen.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.0.</note> Nor can any man have an intereſt in any one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe for himſelf or ſeed, without an intereſt in Chriſt: there never was or will be any Covenant betwixt God and Man ſince the fall, but through Chriſt: he then that hath Chriſt, hath ſomething to plead for his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren more than another hath:<note place="margin">Col. 3.11</note> he only <hi>is all and in all for our ſelves and ours; And they ſhall hang on him all the glory of his Fathers Houſe, the off-ſpring and the iſſue, all veſſels of ſmall quantity.</hi> Iſa. 22.24. All believers are Gods family, and by Faith in Prayer they may freely hang upon him <hi>off-ſpring, i. e.</hi> Children, Grand-children, the ſmalleſt and leaſt of the Veſſels that are in their houſe he will not refuſe them, but lovingly entertain them; himſelf will take Infants into his Arms, as himſelf being an Infant, was taken into old <hi>Simeons</hi> Arms, and both old and young are bleſſed by him. Oh happy Parents that lay ſurvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſeed in ſo warm a boſom! they cannot miſcarry that have Chriſt for their Guardian.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Another Legacy that Parents may leave their Children is the third perſon of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Trinity, the Holy Ghoſt, Iſa. 44.3, 4. <hi>For I will pour Water upon him that is thirſty. I will pour my Spirit upon thy Seed, and my bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon thine off-ſpring, and they ſhall ſpring
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:108774:23"/> up as among the graſs, as willows by the water courſes:</hi> There's no intereſt in God or Chriſt but by the operation of the Spirit: the Holy Ghoſt proceeding from Father and Son, <hi>teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> believers <hi>all things,</hi> convinceth of <hi>Sin,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neweth the will,<note place="margin">Joh. 14.16, 26.16.8, 13.</note> begetteth faith, uniteth the Soul to God, filleth the empty veſſel with divine gifts, graces, influences, comforts; all the good things of Heaven are conveyed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Soul by our Lords ſubſtitute, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit aſſiſteth, quickneth, inlargeth, ſupporteth and ſatisfieth; yea ſaith the Chriſtian, I have had much experience of the Spirits help in my own Soul, but what reaſon have I to hope for the like to my Children? Look on the text again, <hi>I will pour my Spirit upon thy Seed:</hi> it ſhall not come on them by drops, but be poured on them abundantly: they ſhall be filled with the Holy Ghoſt, ſee the full pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe in <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28. accompliſhed, Act. 2.17, 18. <hi>I will pour out my Spirit upon all fleſh, and your Sons and Daughters ſhall Prophecy.</hi> It's true there's ſomething in that Promiſe Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and extraordinary, ſuited to that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, but ſomething there is alſo uſual, permanent and eſſentially neceſſary to true Chriſtianity: which God makes good to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers and their ſeed in all ages. Oh happy Children! that have <hi>the Grace of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the love of God, and the communion</hi> and communications <hi>of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 13.14.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Children of Believers are rightful heirs of all Goſpel-priviledges: I may in a ſound
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:108774:23"/> ſenſe ſay of them as <hi>Paul</hi> of the Jewiſh Church, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4. who are Iſraelites, to whom pertaineth the Adoption, and the glory, and the Covenants, and the giving of the Law, and the ſervice of God, and the Promiſes: there are two ſorts of priviledges. 1. External as the Ordinances; they being born within the Pale of the Viſible Church, have the Prayers of Gods People for them.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.11.</note> As the Children of <hi>Abraham</hi> had <hi>the Seal of Circumciſion, at eight days old,</hi> ſo Children of Believers are <hi>Baptized,</hi> being <hi>Diſciples of Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> and ſo have Gods Sheep-mark ſet upon them betimes, and are taken into his peculiar pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and growing up, and owning their Baptiſmal Covenant, they enjoy, 2. Thoſe Eſſential Priviledges that accompany Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as Reconciliation, Adoption, Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and are in a fair way to Eternal Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, for they lye in the Road of Free-grace, under the droppings of the Sanctuary, where the Spirit is wont to breathe the breath of Spiritual Life: if any be proper heirs of Gods ſpecial care, and Ordinances, ſurely it's the Children of Gods People, Pſal. 69.35, 36. <hi>For God will ſave</hi> Zion, <hi>and build the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of</hi> Judah: who ſhall have the benefit of this Salvation? He anſwers, the Seed alſo of his Servants ſhall inherit it, and they that love his name ſhall dwell therein; Parents have pray'd for the Churches Deliverance, and their Children ſhall reap the fruit of their Prayers, ſo Pſal. 102.28. <hi>The Children of thy Servants ſhall continue, and their Seed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:108774:24"/> ſhall be eſtabliſhed before thee:</hi> there's a double mercy here; 1. In reſtoring Ordinances, 2. In vouchſafing this priviledge to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Believers. Oh what would a Child of God give to know that his Poſterity ſhould ſee better days? You have it in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and may have it in the performance, if you reach out the hand of Faith to receive it, for your ſelves and yours.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Children of Believing Parents ſhall be converted to God by Ordinances. Pſal. 110. 3. <hi>The People ſhall be willing in the day of thy Power (i. e.</hi> in diſpenſing of powerful Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances) <hi>in the beauties of holineſs,</hi> [for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs is full of glory] <hi>from the Womb of the Morning [i. e.</hi> from the beginning of Chriſts entrance upon his Kingdom] <hi>thou haſt the Dew of thy Youth, [i. e.</hi> thoſe young men of the Seed of the faithful that ſhall be born to the Meſſiah, reſembling Dew for quality and quantity, for number and ſtrange manner of Genaration. But a plainer text we have in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.22, 23. Jacob <hi>ſhall not now be aſhamed, neither ſhall his Face now wax pale</hi> [through the loſs of good blood, or death of godly] <hi>But when he ſeeth his Children the work of my hands, in the midſt of him, they ſhall ſanctifie my name</hi>— Oh bleſſed ſight! to behold Gods Image and Workmanſhip in the Souls of our Children! this is far better than to behold our Image upon them: Gods Picture is drawn by his own hand, with the Pencil of his Word and Spirit: the diſcovery of this will raiſe high Monuments to the glory of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:108774:24"/> Free-grace: <hi>Lift up thine Eyes</hi> (ſaith God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.45.) <hi>Thy Sons ſhall come from far, and thy daughters ſhall be nurſed at thy ſide;</hi> I know it means Gentlie-converts: And 'tis ſo much the more of concern to us.<note place="margin">Iſa. 49.22.</note> Another text ſaith <hi>they ſhall bring thy Sons in their arms, with great care and tenderneſs as nurſes carry young infants in their boſoms that they be not hurt.</hi> Oh what a brave ſight is it to ſee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts flocking to Chriſt, and into his Church <hi>like doves to their windows or lockers!</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 60.8</note> the Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Tranſlate it <hi>as Doves with their young ones unto me:</hi> You may hope for your childrens ſaving converſion, having thoſe encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing promiſes.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Godly Perſons natural Children may and ſhall be uſeful inſtruments of publick good to the Church of God, <hi>Iſa</hi> 49.17. <hi>Thy Children ſhall make haſte,</hi> (or as others ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it,) <hi>thy builders:</hi> And her Children were her <hi>builders,</hi> as we read in <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah:</hi> That is a glorious day, when deſtroyers are gone, and the Churches Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren build Zions Temple and Walls: But ſo it ſhall be, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.12. <hi>And they that ſhall be of thee (i. e.</hi> thy Children Spiritual or Natural, or both) <hi>ſhall build the old Waſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, thou ſhalt raiſe the Foundations of many generations.</hi> Is not this worth ſomething to have bleſſed Inſtruments of Reformation raiſed out of your loyns, as Magiſtrates or Miniſters! how did it glad <hi>Davids</hi> heart, that his Son <hi>Solomon</hi> muſt build God an houſe, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.13. <hi>He ſhall build an houſe for my
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:108774:25"/> name.</hi> David ecchos', verſe 18. <hi>Who am I, O Lord God, and what is my houſe that thou haſt brought me hitherto?</hi> And what if a <hi>Zerobbabel</hi> or a <hi>Joſhuah</hi> proceed out of thy loyns, who knows but ſome of thy poſterity may be raiſed up as godly Miniſters to convert ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to God? hope and pray, for all things are poſſible with God, and thou haſt incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement from the Covenant.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> More grounds of incouragement to Parents from the Promiſes.</head>
               <p n="7">7 ANother incourageing word to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents for their Children is, that principles of grace and profeſſion of godlineſs ſhall continue to future generations, <hi>Iſa?</hi> 59.21. <hi>As for me, this is my Covenant with them, ſaith the Lord, my Spirit that is upon thee and my words which I have put in thy mouth ſhall not depart out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of thy ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ednor out of the mouth of thy Seeds Seed, ſaith the Lord, from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth and for ever.</hi> This is a large and long-laſting charter: God Spirits within his children, and the owning of his name in their lips, and this for ever! What can godly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents deſire more? Whether this Spirit im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a Spirit of Prophecy or a Spirit of San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, ſurely it's a rich kindneſs, that it ſhall run in this ſtraight line, and channel
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:108774:25"/> to many generations, that the name of God, as well as your name may be kept up in your Family perpetually when you are dead and gone: Oh happy Parents that have ſuch Children! Happy Children that had ſuch Parents! and bleſſed be God that embraceth both in the boſom of the Covenant! That's a Soul-ſupporting word in <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the word that I covenanted with</hi> [your Fathers, yea with] <hi>you, when you came out of</hi> Egypt, <hi>ſo my Spirit remaineth among you:</hi> Fear ye not, be not daunted, there were as many and great obſtructions in the way of mercy then as now, yet grace overcame them, and I have not taken away my Spirit from you notwithſtanding your multiplied provocations this 2000. years, but ſtill it is among you and ſhall continue to many gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations: May not faith triumph in this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe?</p>
               <p n="8">8. That great obſervations ſhall be made of and remarks upon the Children of godly Parents, <hi>Iſa</hi> 61.8, 9. <hi>I will make an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Covenant with them, and their ſeed ſhall be among the gentiles</hi> (i. e. Gentile Churches) <hi>and their off-ſpring among the People, all that ſee them ſhall acknowledg them, that they are the ſeed which the Lord hath bleſſed.</hi> Men ſhall ſpeak to each other, Do not you ſee the faithful child of ſuch a believing Father? Oh how many a precious day have we had, with ſuch an ones Father, Mother, or Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father! this is the Pious Child of a Zealous father, you ſee it's not in vain to ſeek and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:108774:26"/> ſerve God, I remember the prayers and tears poured out for his Child, and I ſee the bleſſed fruit thereof: God is a prayer-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God: of ſome Children we may ſay, as <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.5. <hi>When I call to remembrance the unfeigned faith that is in thee, which dwelt firſt in thy Grand-mother</hi> Lois, <hi>and thy Mother</hi> Eunice, <hi>and I am perſuaded that in thee alſo:</hi> His Grandmothers name was <hi>Lois,</hi> which ſignifies better, his Mothers name <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> ſignifying victor, and <hi>Timothy</hi> is the fear of God: If Parents chuſe the better part, God will give them victory over the World, Sin, and Satan, yea they ſhall have power with God, and obtain God-fearing Children, which others will obſerve and admire the grace of God in.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Childrens Children to many generations are remembered with Covenant-kindneſs: So in the ſecond Commandment, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.6. <hi>Shewing mercy unto thouſands</hi> [i. e. of generations,] <hi>of them that love me and keeep my Commandments:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 7.9.</note> This is tranſcendent mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, puniſhment extending but to three or four of them, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. you'll ſay, mercy and juſtice are Gods two Arms, is the one longer than the other? Anſwer no, they are equally infinite, but he maketh his Church to feel more of his mercy, then of his juſtice, <hi>with the Lord there is mercy,</hi> why ſo? Becauſe <hi>with him is plenteous Redemption,</hi> Pſal. 130.7. It is a Covenant of Grace, and Chriſt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth as Mediator of it: Oh! the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowings
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:108774:26"/> of Free-grace to many generations, Pſal. 103.17, 18. <hi>But the mercy of the Lord is from everlaſting to everlaſting upon them that fear him, and his righteouſneſs unto Childrens Children.</hi> Mark it, it's called righteouſneſs, to ſhew, it is a diſcharge of his obligation, by which he hath in ſome ſort bound himſelf to Parents to do good to their Poſterity,<note place="margin">Mic. 7.20.</note> for it was mercy to <hi>Abraham</hi> to make a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, but it is truth and faithfulneſs to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it to <hi>Jacob.</hi> and his riſing ſeed many years after: for 'tis founded in his Eternal purpoſe, and continues to Eternity: and this is the reaſon of our hopes of the calling the <hi>Jews,</hi> becauſe they are beloved for their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſake, or rather becauſe of God's Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with their Anceſtors, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.27, 28. Oh what incouragement is this to Parents that God will not utterly caſt off their ſeed: but will reſume thoughts of love to them at laſt?</p>
               <p n="10">10. That God will reduce the wandring Children of his People by ſeaſonable and ſanctified correction, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.29.—35.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 7.14, 15.</note> 
                  <hi>If his Children for ſake my Law and walk not in my judgments</hi> (i. e. if they forfeit the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges promiſed by non-performance of the conditions) <hi>then will I viſit their tranſgreſſion with a Rod, and their iniquity with Stripes, nevertheleſs my loving kindneſs will I not utterly take from him nor ſuffer my faithfulneſs to fail:</hi> God hath adopted Affliction to be a branch of Covenant affection,<note place="margin">Pſa;l. 119.75.</note> 'Its a promiſe [I will viſit] not ſo much a threatning, for in faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:108774:27"/> he afflicts his Children: he will not take ſo much pains with a ſlave as with a Son: he will make his Children thank God for a whipping, Lord; ſaith a godly Parent, bring home my Child though it be by weeping croſs: ſtarve my prodigal ſon, or feed him with husks, that he may reflect on his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers plenteous Table: oh break his Leg or Arm rather than damn his Soul: caſt him on a ſick bed, rather than caſt him into Hell: let his Purgatory be here and his Heaven hereafter: now our gracious God anſwers his Childrens Prayers: good <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for his extravagant Son <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> were anſwered by Gods taking him among the Thorns, binding him with Fetters, carrying him to <hi>Babylon,</hi> till he had humbled him to purpoſe, and made him know that Jehovah was God, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.11, 12, 13. doubtleſs the natural as well as the ſpiritual Father of the Prodigal will welcome home the Child, tho' broken on the Wheel.</p>
               <p n="11">11. The Covenant ingageth for a bleſſing on Parents inſtruction and correction of their erring Children: this is of great uſe, 1. For inſtruction, Prov. 22.6. <hi>Train up a Child in the way he ſhould go:</hi> [There's the Parents Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, do thy duty to ſet him right in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his way, ſo ſome read it,] <hi>and when he is old he will not depart from it, i. e.</hi> not eaſily, ordinarily, <hi>q. d.</hi> if thou that art the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wilt do thy duty faithfully, I will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to do my part: ſet thou their faces in the right road, and I will keep them in it; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:108774:27"/> I will bleſs thy inſtructions admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, counſels, examples, ſee <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. God ſaith of Abraham, <hi>I know him that he will command his Children, and his houſhold after him,</hi> you'll ſay what is he better for that? they'll chuſe whether they'll obey or no: nay ſaith God, but I will undertake for them, <hi>[And they ſhall keep the way of the Lord, to do Juſtice and Judgment.]</hi> His labour ſhall not be in vain; I live, ſaith God, to make his words take impreſſion on his ſurviving Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren when he is dead? For correction you have a notable promiſe in Prov. 23.13, 14. <hi>With-hold not correction from the Child, for if thou beateſt him with the rod, he ſhall not dye</hi> [I will take care of him;] <hi>thou ſhalt beat him with the Rod, and ſhall deliver his Soul from Hell:</hi> O bleſſed whipping! ſurely ſuch a ſcourge as fetcheth blood is eaſier than hell-torments: but my benediction ſhall be upon that correction: that's a cruel Parent, that will rather ſee his Child a flaming Faggot in the ſcorching fire, than try to whip folly out of him, that's cruel pity, better he ſhould cry here, then roar hereafter, yea and curſe thee for ever, that wouldſt not ſpeak a word or give him a tap, to prevent theſe intoler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able torments: Oh the good that ſeaſonable correction may do! if thou prevail not to make thy Child good, yet thou wilt have comfort in the diſcharge of thy duty, there's good hopes of both by the bleſſing of God, Prov. 29.17. <hi>Correct thy Son, and he ſhall give thee reſt, yea he ſhall give delight unto thy Soul:</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:108774:28"/> yet take this caution, that theſe promiſes muſt not be underſtood abſolutely, neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, and univerſally producing this effect, but ordinarily ſo it is, and this is ſufficient motive to Parents to do their duty, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement therein.</p>
               <p n="12">12. The laſt incouragement to Parents from the Covenant of God, for their ſurvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Children, is, that God will take care of their outward concerns in the World, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.7. the juſt man walketh in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, his Children are bleſſed after him, if their Father hath not heaped up riches by cunning and covetous devices, and ſo leaves them but little in the World, yet he hath left them in the hands of a good Father, who will take care of them, when their earthly Parents are gone: for this bleſſed Covenant is not confined to the perſons of the Godly but entailed on their Poſterity, Pſal 112.1, 2. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth the Lord, that delighteth greatly in his commandments, his ſeed ſhall be mighty upon earth, the generation of the upright ſhall be bleſſed:</hi> anſwerable to this, I call to mind a paſſage, told me by a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Miniſter in <hi>London,</hi> who knew a poor and pious Preacher in <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> who had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Children, and little to maintain them, one askt him, how he thought they could ſhift when he was gone, he anſwered, I am not at all afraid of that, I am more afraid of them when they ſhall ride up and down <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> ſtreets in their Coaches: which came to paſs, for ſome of them came to be Aldermen
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:108774:28"/> of that Famous City: our frequent experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence confirms this truth, what care God takes of his upright-hearted Servants Seed when they are laid in the duſt: let us take holy <hi>David</hi>'s Experiment, Pſal. 37.25. <hi>I have been young, and now am old, yet have I not ſeen the righteous forſaken, nor his ſeed begging bread.</hi> If there have been ſome few excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, theſe yet do not deſtroy the truth of a general propoſition: howbeit temporal promiſes were more expreſs and poſitive to the Jews of old, than to chriſtians in Goſpel-times, which conſiſts more in ſpirituals: But this will remain a truth that Children of Godly Parents are uſually provided for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably even in things that concern this life, if it tends to Gods glory, and their good, and if God ſee it good in his Infinite Wiſdom, which limitations muſt always be annexed to temporal promiſes: but if they be poor, defamed, ſick, in priſons, baniſhed, yet <hi>all theſe work together for their good.</hi> Rom. 8.28.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> An Anſwer to an Objection againſt the premiſes.</head>
               <p>THE third general head in the Doctrinal part, is an anſwer to a main objection, which is this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> You have produced many promiſes as branches of the Goſpel-covenant, that the children of godly Parents, ſhall have convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:108774:29"/> Grace, that God the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt ſhall be theirs, are heirs of Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Priviledges, ſhall be ſanctified, be uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful inſtruments in the Church, ſhall own their profeſſion with an holy converſation, if they wander God will reduce them, bleſs Parents inſtructions, corrections, take care of their outward concerns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now do we not ſee by daily obſervation the clean contrary to all theſe, how many worthy Miniſters have had worthleſs ſons! how many worthleſs Children are there of gracious Parents? nay do we not ſee ſome Children of Godly Parents, miſcarry more than others of their carnal civil neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours more proud, ſcorners of Godlineſs, companions of Drunkards, Swearers, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucht perſons that have proved a great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour to God, ſcandal to Religion, grief to Godly, and Heart-breaking to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, yea have ſo prejudiced the Spirits of wicked men, that they ſay, this Religion is but a fancy, praying ſo much is needleſs, and what's become of the Covenant you ſo much boaſt of? Nay, have we not ſeen ſome Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Godly Parents live and dye viſibly graceleſs, under tokens of Gods Wrath, yea haſtning their death by intemperance and overmuch wickedneſs? How is this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with all that you have ſpoken? How is God true to his Covenant?</p>
               <p>This is a ſad truth, and cannot be denied and an awful conſideration, and poſſibly hath ſtaggered the Faith of ſome, and ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:108774:29"/> the hands of ſome wicked againſt the power of Godlineſs, and is too palpable an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation to be denied. But yet I hope to clear this tremendous providence from the holy Scriptures by propounding theſe ſeven conſiderations.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some of the Children of Gods People can ſet their ſeal to Gods faithfulneſs, in the Covenant made to their Parents and their Seed: this clears Gods truth and the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Religion: I doubt not but ſome Children of the Covenant can ſpeak the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of <hi>Solomon,</hi> in 1 Kin. 8.23, 24. <hi>Lord God of</hi> Iſrael <hi>there is no God like unto thee, who keepeſt Covenant and Mercy with thy Servants that walk before thee with all their heart, who haſt kept with thy Servant</hi> David <hi>my Father, that thou promiſedſt him, thou ſpakeſt alſo with thy mouth, and haſt fulfill'd it with thine hand as it is this day:</hi> will not ſome ſtand forth and ſay, I bleſs God for God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Parents, my Soul hath found the benefit of their Prayers, and fruit of Gods Promiſe, I prefer this charter to all earthly priviledges: let others ſay their pleaſure, I will for ever adore Free-grace, that brought me forth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo good a Covenant, it's better to me than to be born of a Royal Race, and being Heir to a Crown, <hi>he is my God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 15.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and I will prepare him an habitation, my Fathers God, and I will exalt him:</hi> and cannot ſome Parents ſay,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 7.19.</note> God hath <hi>ſpoken well of his ſervants houſe for a great while to come?</hi> behold I ſee the buds of Grace in this or that Child, and a ſaving growing work in another: bleſſed be
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:108774:30"/> Free-grace: I can hold forth this token for good againſt all the cavils of prophane Spirits, and againſt my own unbelieving fears.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God never forſakes the Children of Godly Parents, till they forſake him; poor Children run away from God before he turn them off, 1 Chron. 28.9. <hi>If thou ſeek him he will be found of thee, but if thou forſake him he will cast thee off for ever.</hi> If <hi>Solomon</hi> (or any other Child or Children of a Godly Father,) put on a Cloak of Religion, to pleaſe Parents or accompliſh a carnal end, while they live, and caſt off Religion, and perverſly turn their backs on God, and embrace wicked ways, without true Repentance, they have diſcharged God of his performing promiſe, becauſe they have voluntarily deſcarded the condition on their part; now at ripe age, when they are fit to make a choice, it's a voluntary act, proceeding from their own wilfulneſs,<note place="margin">John 5.40.</note> 
                  <hi>You will not come unto me;</hi> and then it becomes a judicial act in God to forſake them, becauſe they firſt forſook him: and neither they nor their Parents can find fault with God for withdrawing from them that Grace they abuſed, which he is not bound to give them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Parents have no reaſon to challenge God for non-performance of the terms of the Covenant, but themſelves for their neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of duty to their Children, this is ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily the reaſon of their Childrens miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: even godly Parents are too apt to miſs it, by over fondneſs, and negligence in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:108774:30"/> their education, not admoniſhing, counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, correcting them; <hi>David</hi> had been too indulgent to <hi>Adonijah,</hi> in not croſſing him, and doubtleſs his Conſcience flew in his Face upon his Ambition: this is a plain caſe, good <hi>Eli</hi> honoured his ſons above God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.29. by permitting them to diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him, chuſing rather to offend God by connivance at their ſin, than diſpleaſe them by ſevere rebukes, effectual reſtraints, and ſevere puniſhments, for as a Father, and as a Magiſtrate he ought to have curbed them: therefore God ſaith, <hi>I will judge his houſe for ever, for the iniquity which he knoweth of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his ſons made themſelves vile, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained them not.</hi> Oh what privy nips do the Conſciences of Parents give them, when their Children grow up and take not good ways! alas I ſinned againſt God, and now God leaves them to themſelves; I have no cauſe to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure God, but condemn my ſelf: God is Righteous, their ſin is a Glaſs to ſee my own. Lord humble me, and convince them, oh pardon my iniquity, that I may pray believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly for my Seed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. God may paſs by the immediate off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of his faithful Children and work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their more remote poſterity: Free grace ſometimes runs under ground for a ſeaſon and breaks out at a diſtance, an immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Son is bad, but grace layes hold on a Grandſon, <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> was a good man, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.32. But <hi>Jehoram</hi> his Son proved bad, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.6. Yea, <hi>Ahaziah</hi> his Son
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:108774:31"/> walked in the ways of the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.3, 4. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> did right in the ſight of the Lord, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.4. And <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham</hi> his Son, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 27.2, 6. But had a bad Son <hi>Ahaz,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.1, 2. Yet Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing love broke out again in good <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.2. But it lay dormant for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable time, and laid not hold of <hi>Manaſſeh.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.2. Yea ſome think his forc'd Repentance was not ſincere and ſaving; however the grace of God withdrew from <hi>Amon</hi> his Son, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.20. But laid hold on good <hi>Joſiah</hi> his Son, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.2. You ſee how grace skips and leaps over the head of one, and lays its hand upon another, yea ſometimes it croſſeth hands and as <hi>Jacob</hi> guided his hands wittingly laying his right hand on <hi>Ephraim</hi> and his left hand on <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 48.14, 20.</note> ſetting the younger before the Elder, contrary to <hi>Joſephs</hi> deſire and deſign: Thus God croſſeth our natural affections and expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons bleſſing ſuch as we leaſt thought of and leaving others that our hearts were moſt ſet upon, to convince us of the freeneſs of his grace: But thus his Covenant doth ſtand ſure.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Delays are no denials: God hath his time to bring in the Prodigal Sons of pious Parents; <hi>[nullum tempus occurrit Regi]</hi> the King of Heaven can take what time he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to work on hearts. <hi>Saul</hi> ſhall long per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the Church, yet become a choſen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel: it's worth obſerving that the Children of many godly Parents ſowed their wild
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:108774:31"/> Oats in youth; even godly <hi>Jacob</hi> was guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of many faults, ſtealing the bleſſing by a lye: Several of <hi>Jacobs</hi> Sons had foul ſpots, <hi>Ruben</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> were guilty of Inceſt, <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> of raſh Anger, Treachery, Murder; yet all godly Patriarchs: Several combining out of envy to ſell <hi>Joſeph:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they broke their Father <hi>Jacob</hi>'s honeſt heart; but let not godly Parents make too haſty concluſions: He that believes makes not haſte: It may be God defers to hear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he loves your company, and would make you an Errand to the throne of grace, your Prayers are yet too cold, he thinks fit to quicken importunity: the Anſwer will come double loaden, and pay for all your pains and patience; give God the glory of his wiſdom: he knows how to husband your mercies better than you: it's worth obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that thoſe Women in Sacred Writ that waited longeſt for Children had the beſt as <hi>Sarah, Rebecca, Rachel, Hannah, Manoahs</hi> Wife, and <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> Be not prepoſterous, you may ſee Gods Salvation before you die.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If God never ſhews mercy to your ſeed, you muſt not ſo much murmur at his Juſtice, as adore his Soveraignty; he is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute diſpoſer of his own grace; ſuch an act of Prerogative may be admired muſt, not be queſtioned: The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> having waded as far as Scripture led him into the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathomable Abyſs of God's caſting of the Covenanted ſeed of believing <hi>Abraham,</hi> and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:108774:32"/> adopting the forlorn, and forſaken Gentiles, ſtands on the bank of that Ocean and cries, [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] <hi>Oh the depth of the riches both of the wiſdom and knowledge of God!</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ro. 11.33.</note> 
                  <hi>how unſearchable are his judgments and his ways paſt finding out:</hi> The immenſity and ineffability of theſe counſels are ſuch depths, as he ſaith in <hi>Job</hi> 32.13. <hi>He giveth not account of any of his matters:</hi> They are oft unaccountable, but never unrighteous: Kings have <hi>[Arcana Imperij,]</hi> miſteries of State, not fit to be communicated to vulgar capacities: And much more the infinit God;<note place="margin">Deut. 29.29.</note> 
                  <hi>ſecret things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to God:</hi> It's preſumption to pry into Gods Ark, our weak eyes cannot behold this glorious Sun: poor ſinner, down on thy knees, and ſay thus to God; Lord, I will rather adimire the riches of thy grace to my own Soul, than quarrel with thee for not giving my Child grace: It is an abſtruſe, and inſcrutable depth, my humble Ignorance or neſcience ſhall ſtop at thy pleaſure, my will ſhall be melted into thy will; if my ſeed muſt glory in thy Juſtice, I will acquieſce therein and ſay, though <hi>clouds and darkneſs are round about thee, yet righteouſneſs and judgment are the habitations of thy throne,</hi> Pſal. 97.2.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Yet for all this Religion muſt be own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and vindicated, <hi>God is good to the Soul that ſeeks him;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 45.9.</note> to the Soul <hi>that waits for him:</hi> He never ſaid to the ſeed of <hi>Jacob, ſeek ye me in vain.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lam. 3.25.</note> If God never ſhew mercy to any of my ſeed, yet I will never juſtifie the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:108774:32"/> wicked, by ſaying <hi>It's in vain to ſerve God:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 3.14.</note> No, God forbid, Il wil never ſay, that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erleſs Families are as good as praying Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, my own experience, and thouſands more beſides; the infallible verity of the faithful God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.11.</note> will contradict that Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Maxim: <hi>in the keeping Gods commandments I have found great reward;</hi> Yea I have found that the miſcarriage of my Child (which is the greateſt croſs that ever I met with) hath been bleſſed for the good of my Soul, as the good Woman ſaid, bearing my Children, and my croſſes have coſt me dear, but I could not be without either; it's not fit I ſhould chuſe my affliction, and what God lays on is welcome, and I will like Chriſt no worſe for his Croſs: for I find theſe bitter Waters moſt medicinal, and the ſweeteſt fruit grows on this bitter Tree: the badneſs of my Child hath helpt to make me better: this heart-breaking hath proved an heart melting: it's true, wicked men are hardened by ſeeing the Children of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant thus miſcarry, (even as diviſions,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.34, 35. 2 Cor. 2.14.</note> and offences amongſt Gods people, are occaſions of their ruine, yea the Goſpel-preaching is the <hi>ſavour of Death</hi> to ſome) but as God is juſt therein to them, ſo my Soul hath cauſe to bleſs the Phyſitian of Souls, that ſo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers this poiſon, as to make it wholeſome Phyſick to my poor Soul: my croſſes are better than their comforts. I will commend Religion, though I mourn over my irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:108774:33"/> Child: Godlineſs is gain, though I gain not Grace for my Child by it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> An <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Conviction and Humiliation.</head>
               <p>ALL the improvement I ſhall make of this point, ſhall be 1. Of Conviction. 2. Exhortation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Of Conviction, if this be true, that notwithſtanding the ſins and ſufferings in a godly mans family, which occaſion much grief to his Spirit, yet he is comforted and ſatisfied in Gods gracious Goſpel-covenant.</p>
               <p>Then it follows by the rule of contraries, that thoſe Families that have no right to this Goſpel-covenant are in a woful ſtate, have no grounds of comfort, ſatisfaction, no hopes of Salvation, ſo remaining, they are not under a bleſſing, but under a curſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.33. The curſe of the Lord is in the houſe of the wicked: the Plague is in that houſe: ſet a croſs on that door, and ſay Lord have mercy upon it: wicked families, read your doom, and train of curſes in <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.15, 16, 17, 18, 19. you make great reckoning of your eſtates, alas there's no Covenant bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in any thing you have, they are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves great bleſſings of God, but to you they are curſed, Mat. 2.2. <hi>If you will not hear, and if ye will not lay it to heart, to give glory to my name, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, I will even ſend
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:108774:33"/> a curſe upon you, and will curſe your bleſſings, yea I have curſed them already, becauſe ye do not lay it to heart:</hi> it's a dreadful flaming text againſt impenitent, inconſiderate ſinners: not only their perſons, but all their dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick concerns are under a curſe; your meat, money, houſes, wives, children, garments, imployments, injoyments, all that you do, all that you have ſhall be accurſed; this is an heavy caſe: a grounded curſe by man lyes long, and lights ſadly upon Succeſſors; <hi>Noah</hi> pronounced a curſe on <hi>Cham</hi>'s off-ſpring,<note place="margin">Gen. 9.25.</note> which never left them till it rooted out the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites,</hi> by <hi>Shem</hi>'s Poſterity.</p>
               <p>The ſubject is large and aſtoniſhing, I ſhall ſay ſomething,
<list>
                     <item>1. To Irreligious Parents.</item>
                     <item>2. To Irreligious Children.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. There are ſome Parents within the bounds of the viſible Church, that, 1. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not this Covenant, never ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to conſider it: they bring their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants to be baptized in a cuſtom, becauſe others do ſo, and it would be a ſhame not to have them Chriſtened, Neighbours would cry out againſt them; but they neither know the meaning of Baptiſm, nor Covenant, nor have they any mind to know them. 2. Take no pains to get their own Souls intereſted in this Covenant,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.12.</note> but are <hi>ſtrangers from the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants of Promiſe,</hi> and ſo have no hope for themſelves or ſeed: we find great fault with prodigal Parents that imbezel, and alienate their Anceſtors Inheritance, that ſhould have
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:108774:34"/> deſcended to their Children, but it's a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times worſe for Parents, to cut off this bleſſed entail of the Goſpel-covenant. 3. Moſt are negligent in doing their duty to Children, alas how few will take pains to inſtruct them in the principles of Religion, the nature, uſe, ends of the Seals of the Covenant, in praying for them, as if there were no ſuch text in the Bible, or they had never made ſuch a promiſe,<note place="margin">Eph. 6.4.</note> 
                  <hi>to bring them up in the nurture and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of the Lord!</hi> Ah! wretched Father, Mother, out of your own mouth are you condemned, that promiſe what you never intend to perform: how notoriouſly do you falſifie your promiſe, betray your truſt. 4. There are too too many Parents that are ſcandalous, prophane, atheiſtical, and teach their young ones to lye, ſwear, be drunk, unclean, by the evil example they ſet before them. A Child brought up with <hi>Plato,</hi> coming home, hearing his father in a furious paſſion, could ſay, I never ſaw or heard the like in <hi>Plato.</hi> Alas, ſirs you leſſen your eſteem with your Children by ſinful courſes; you bring guilt upon your family: yea you do your endeavour to root out your family: <hi>The ſeed of the wicked ſhall be cut off,</hi> Pſal. 37.28. The whole <hi>Pſalm,</hi> and daily experience te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies the ſame:<note place="margin">Hab. 2.10.</note> Ah ſinner, <hi>thou haſt conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhame to thy houſe,</hi> and ſome generations hence may reap the fruits of thy folly. The text ſaith <hi>he will viſit the iniquity of the Fathers upon the Children to the third and fourth genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them that hate him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 20.5.</note> There are ſome
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:108774:34"/> hereditary ſins, and ſome hereditary puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments bequeathed as an heritage to their Children; Divines vindicate Gods Juſtice in proving that God may righteouſly puniſh ſins of Relations in their correlates,<note place="margin">Filij ſunt res Parentum.</note> for Children (ſay ſome) are portions of Parents, as people are the riches and good of Princes: yea they have in them <hi>[aliquid parentis]</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Parent, they are pieces of them. So <hi>David</hi> was puniſhed in his Childs death: But I ſhall not ſpend more time in this point; becauſe ſomuch is ſaid by many others.</p>
               <p>How can you ſee your Children damned in Hell through your default? How can you hear their cries, and ſee their torments in that Infernal Lake, gnaſhing their Teeth, and roaring with Flames about their Ears, ſaying, oh curſed Parents, that by your Soul-damning negligence, have brought your ſelves and me into this lamentable ſtate! that would not ſpeak a word to me, nor plead the Covenant for me, to prevent theſe Eternal Torments: that ſaw me go on in ſin, and would not ſtop my courſe betimes, by faithful admonition and ſound correction; nay that ſet me a bad Example, and were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that I ſhould periſh with you, curſed be the day that ever I ſhould know ſuch wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Parents, well had it been for me, that I had never been born, or had been brought forth a Beaſt without a rational Soul, that I might have died like a Beaſt, yea I had been comparatively happy if you my Parents had put me to death, or as the Heathen <hi>Thraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> lamenting my Birth, buried me betimes,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:108774:35"/> and rejoyced at my death, becauſe of the miſeries of humane life, but Oh I am brought forth, and fed up for the murderer, the murderer of Souls; I had but gone (as a condemned perſon) out of a dark priſon to the place of Execution, but now, having lived thus long in the World, I have fought againſt God, and ſunk my Soul deeper in Hell: Oh wo is me, that I lived under ſuch cruel Tyrants, and as the dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſon ſaid, I am going to Hell and my wicked Mother muſt follow after.</p>
               <p>And Oh, the woful reſentment of fellow damned Parents upon the hideous outcries of the fruit of their own bodies and bowels! here neighbours fare is not good fare, but the rich mans torments are aggravated by his fine brethrens coming into the ſame condemnation: Every Screek of the Child will tear the heart of the ſelf-condemning Father: how eaſily might I have prevented theſe deſpairing groans by a faithful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of duty! What if I had followed my wandring Child with ſighs and tears to God and him while there was hope, but now all too late, all too late, the guilt of my Childs blood is now required at my hands, Had I whipt him ſo as to fetch blood at every laſh, it had not been ſo dreadful as the laſhes of divine vengeance; had I diſinhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited him for his faults, it had not been ſo confounding, as my own being baniſht with him from the preſence of the Lord and from the glory of his power, Oh! what is tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:108774:35"/> puniſhment to Eternal torments! Oh that God would ſtrike the hearts of poor carnal Parents with bowels of pity towards their poor periſhing off-ſpring.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Graceleſs irreligious Children, grown up, 'tis no excuſe for you to be bad, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your Parents are bad, are you ſo wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſociable as to go to. Hell for company? This is like the miſerable Indians that leap into their Parents graves to be buried with them: Or like that Italian viſiting his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Sepulcher, waſhing all the parts of the Monument with lamentable tears,<note place="margin">Progenies viperarum nominat po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius quam viperas ut toti ordini exprobret virulentam malitiam to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum corpus damnare vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit. <hi>Calv.</hi> in <hi>Harm.</hi> Evan. in <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.16.</note> fell down dead: God may ſay <hi>who requires this at your hands:</hi> But ſtill it's worſe to follow their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious examples, as too many Children do: You may reverence your Anceſtors, yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine their dictates by the word of truth, and not be as the young Novice entring into a Monaſtery was adviſed <hi>[tu et Aſinus unum eſtote]</hi> to be like an Aſs, ſwallow down all that comes. No, no, you are <hi>redeemed from your vain Converſation,</hi> received by tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition from your Fathers, and therefore muſt enquire not ſimply for the old way, but which is the good way: It's too much what <hi>Cicero</hi> (the Heathen Orator) thinks a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable piece of Religion, to live and die in the Religion of our Anceſtors: It rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Children to take warning by their Fathers falls and faults to avoid them, and the bad Conſequences thereof:<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.14-18.</note> So God ſaith, <hi>If the Father beget a Son, who ſeeth all his Fathers ſins, conſidereth, turneth, he ſhall
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:108774:36"/> not die for his Fathers Iniquity:</hi> But if you follow their ſinful courſes, you juſtifie them, condemn Gods ways, and damn your own Souls: Yea you bring upon your ſelves the guilt of your Fathers ſins beſides your own; wicked Parents are ſet before you as Sea-marks to avoid, not as Land-marks to guide you: The Heathen Orator ſaid, Parents are [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] as houſehold Gods, their words ſhould be as Oracles, but alas they are but men, and may miſtake and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry, but God in his word is an unerring guide: Follow the Lord and you cannot miſs or miſcarry, but you may miſcarry by following the beſt men, you will certainly miſcarry, if you follow bad men: The Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> erroneouſly pleads the place of her Anceſtors worſhip:<note place="margin">John 4.20.</note> And <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> confutes the fooliſh <hi>Jews</hi> fond plea from their Fathers practiſes, <hi>Jer.</hi> 44.17, 21.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall rather hint a few words of conviction to the irreligious Children of godly Parents: Who degenerate from their Anceſtors, that it may be ſaid as in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.16. Abraham <hi>is ignorant of us, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>acknowledgeth us not,</hi> i. e. (as ſome take it) if our godly Anceſtors <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> were now alive, or raiſed up from the dead, they would not own us for their legitimate off-ſpring, we are ſo unlike them. I fear this is too true of the Children of godly Predeceſſors got to reſt, that tread not in their Fathers ſteps, but take a contrary courſe: their Fathers prayed in their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:108774:36"/> but Children have left off that trade, Fathers frequent Religious Societies, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren frequent Alehouſes and naughty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, Fathers walked cloſely with God, Childern run away from God and his Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions: Wo, Wo be to ſuch Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are perjured faedifragous, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworn wretches, who in their Baptiſm in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to be the Lords Servants, Subjects, Souldiers, and to fight under Chriſt's Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner againſt the World, Fleſh and the Devil, and took Preſs-money, but now have turned their backs on Chriſt, and fight the Devils battles againſt Chriſt. Wo be to ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious wretches, what's the doom of ſuch as outrun their Colours but to be ſhot to Death? <hi>Covenant breakers</hi> are ranked amonſt the worſt of Sinners; Heathens, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.31. And ſuch as make hard times in the later days, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3. If it were but a mans Covenant it's a grand crime to diſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nul it, much more this,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.15. Prov. 2.17.</note> the Covenant of Marriage is in ſome ſenſe the Covenant of God, this more immediately and he will avenge the quarrel of his Covenant, <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.25. Oh Sirs! how dare you look God in the face whoſe Covenant ye have broken? What have you to do <hi>to take his Covenant in your mouths,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.16.</note> when Conſcience flies in your face?</p>
               <p n="2">2. You have loſt the benefit of your Infant-Priviledges: Your Infant member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was but calculated for your Infant-State,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:108774:37"/> now you are grown up Adult-perſons, you muſt ſtand upon your own bottoms, no longer on your Parents, now you muſt <hi>live by your own faith;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.17,</note> you muſt enter perſonally into Covenant with God, repent, obey the Goſpel your ſelves, or elſe if thou be a breaker of this Goſpel-Law,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.25.</note> 
                  <hi>thy Circumciſion becomes <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion, i. e.</hi> thy Priviledges are made void, inſignificant: So God reckons uncircumciſed in Heart with uncircumciſed in fleſh, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.26. And ſaith they are <hi>as the Children of the</hi> Aethiopians <hi>unto him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amo. 9.7.</note> and in the Goſpel it is repeated again and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Circumciſion is nothing and Uncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is nothing, but the keeping the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.6.15.</note> but <hi>faith which worketh by love; but a new Creature:</hi> You boaſt of your pious Parents, as the <hi>Jews</hi> once did, and bear up big with being <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, alas you may be a <hi>generation of vipers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 3.7, 8, 9.</note> as <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> tells them, and <hi>of your Father the Devil;</hi> as our Lord ſaith,<note place="margin">Joh. 8.33, 44.</note> except you <hi>have the Faith</hi> and <hi>do the works of</hi> Abraham. A famous Family will avail nothing without perſonal piety: Without holineſs in your hearts and lives you cannot be ſaved: think not that God is bound, and you looſe, the Covenant is mutual, reciprocal, you cannot expect the Priviledges without performing the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It's an awful obſervation (and often proves too true) that if the Children of God's People turn Apoſtates they become the worſt of men, and run deeper into ſin,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:108774:37"/> and further from God then many, yea any others: The Sons of good old <hi>Eli</hi> run into unparalleled wickedneſs, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 13, 22. We have many ſad inſtances of <hi>Cain, Cham, Iſhmael, Eſau, Ammon, Abſolom,</hi> yea, <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Rehoboam, Manaſſeh,</hi> and few recovered and with great difficulty; The Tribe of <hi>Dan (Jacobs</hi> Son) turned Idolaters, and ſcarce ever returned to God, therefore are not reckoned amongſt the <hi>Sealed ones, Rom.</hi> 7. 5, 8. Becauſe they ſet up <hi>Micahs</hi> graven Image: and it's obſervable, that <hi>Jonathan</hi> the Son of <hi>Gerſhom (Moſes</hi> Grandſon) was Prieſt to the Tribe of <hi>Dan,</hi> and his Sons after him, until <hi>the day of the captivity of the land,</hi> Judg. 18.30, 31. But the Heathens obſerve that though this <hi>Jonathan</hi> was <hi>Moſes</hi> Natural Grandſon by generation, yet he is called Grandchild of <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> whom he imitated in forgetting God, not of <hi>Moſes</hi> as appears by lifing up a letter in the Hebrew to make it no <hi>Moſes</hi> but <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeh:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> He had ſo far degenerated that his Godly Grandfather muſt not be named with him.<note place="margin">Jer. 5.28.</note> Thus <hi>Iſraelites</hi> are ſaid to overpaſs the deeds of the wicked, <hi>i. e.</hi> of Heathens,<note place="margin">Ezek. 16.47. Ezek. 5.6.</note> yea, they go beyond <hi>Sodom</hi> and her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and change Gods judgments more than the Heathen: The reaſon is clear, becauſe theſe ſin againſt more Light, Love, Helps, Means, Convictions, Godly Examples, Good Education, and therefore are juſtly forſaken of God, and left to greater abominations: Oh tremble leſt this be your caſe.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:108774:38"/>4. The Children of Godly Parents may be caſt into Eternal Torments. <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the Faithful may have an houl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Son in Hell Torment.<note place="margin">Luk. 16.24, 25. Mat. 8.12.</note> The Children of the Kingdom ſhall be caſt out into <hi>utter dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth,</hi> they that would not weep penitently here muſt weep deſpairingly hereafter: they that ſcorned rebukes from Parents, muſt have dreadful rebukes from God and Conſcience, their Education was with Saints, their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion with Devils. There's many gone to Hell with Baptiſmal Water on their Face: Baptized <hi>Magus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 8.13, 20, 23.</note> is like to periſh with his money; he was in the <hi>gall of bitterneſs, and bonds of iniquity,</hi> that dragg'd him to Hell: Yea the damnation of ſuch Caitiffs will be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorſt with more vengeance than others: the Worm of Conſcience will bite harder, being fed with more materials to ſtrengthen her: the Flame will be hotter, having more fewel: the higher men are exalted towards Heaven,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.23.</note> and reach it not, the lower do they fall to Hell, and in Hell; if they plead their birth-right, as he that pleaded he was a Gentleman, the Judge told him, he ſhould therefore have an higher Gallows; or as Lord <hi>Sturton</hi> that was hanged for Murder in a ſilken Halter: ſo muſt theſe well-bred perſons be dealt with,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.47.</note> the more they know of their <hi>Maſters Will,</hi> the more ſtripes are laid on them: the more they glory in their priviledges, the more miſery in their loſs, and the higher their hopes, the greater their diſappointment:
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:108774:38"/> theſe are both hypocrites and apoſtates, whoſe ſin and ſhame is more aggravated and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented than others.<note place="margin">Mat. 24.51.</note> Oh what flaming Fag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gots, and ſcorching Oil, will Parents Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Tears, Councils, Admonitions, Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations be to diſſolute young men! when they ſhall ſee Parents glorified, themſelves condemned: read <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.11, 12, 13.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> An <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Exhortation or Inſtruction.</head>
               <p>THere are four ſorts of perſons concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this Text and Doctrine, that may be inſtructed in their reſpective duties from it.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Viz.</head>
                  <item>1. Children of Uncovenanted Parents.</item>
                  <item>2. Children of Covenanted Parents.</item>
                  <item>3. Perſons married without Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</item>
                  <item>4 Perſons that have a Poſterity.</item>
               </list>
               <p>An hint, and but an hint to all theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There are ſome Children attending on God in Ordinances whoſe immediate Parents were not in Covenant, knew not God, you may lay it to heart and lament it as your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felicity, but this is no bar to your enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment with God: for how can you tell but ſome of your remote Anceſtours might be godly? and if not, Grace is free, <hi>thoſe that come unto him, he will in no wiſe caſt off:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 6.37.</note> you may and muſt venture: ſinners of the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:108774:39"/> Gentiles are grafted into the true Olive,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.24. Jud. 11.1, 2, 27, 28.</note> even contrary to nature, that were Wild by nature, ſo may'ſt thou be. <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phthah</hi> was a Baſtard, thruſt out by his Brethren, but received by God. Be not diſcouraged, though thou be bad,<note place="margin">Col. 3.11. Gal. 3.28.</note> and Parents bad, yet <hi>God is no reſpecter of Perſons;</hi> Barbarian, Scythian, all's one in Chriſt Jeſus; Grace makes, but regards no difference. And if the Grace of God hath leapt over others heads to touch your hearts. 1. Adore the Soveraign actings of Free-grace, give God glory, diſcriminating Grace ſhall have the Crown ſet upon its head: I was doubly polluted in my Birth, from firſt, and immediate Parents. Oh that God ſhould diſpenſe with his ancient law,<note place="margin">Deut. 23.2.</note> that a Baſtard ſhould not enter into the Congregation of the Lord, yet God hath entertained me amongſt his Saints on Earth, and gives me hopes of Heaven, oh wonder of Grace! 2. Be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble all your days, and caſt down in your own eyes. Young profeſſors are apt to be proud, but it ill becomes you of all perſons to be proud, whom God hath lifted from the Dunghill, to ſit with Princes the Kings Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, read and apply, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.18, 19, 20. 3. Make up your Parents defect with your own diligence, what time was loſt in your child-hood and youth, now redeem it, the more ignorant your Parents were, the more knowledge do you lay in. The further they were from God, the nearer do you get to him. The more diſadvantages you have had, the more pains muſt you take for your Souls, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:108774:39"/> it's of abſolute neceſſity. 4. If God have laid hold on your Hearts, be more laborious for the good of your families: you have had ſad experience of the want of careful educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, let not your Children have the like, but inſtruct them, pray for them, do what you can to bring them into Covenant with God, give not them occaſion to complain of your neglect alſo.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Children of Covenanted Parents: God forbid you ſhould act contrary to your Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal Covenant-relation, or contradict your obligations, that Thorns ſhould grow inſtead of Lillies; or ſtinking Weeds, where ſweet ſmelling Flowers have been: it's dreadful, that curſing ſhould be heard where Prayers have been put up, or idle wanton Songs where Hoſanna's have been uſed to the King of Heaven. 1. Review and Renew your Baptiſmal-covenant: you were timely devot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to God in minority, confirm it now at age; you took preſs-money to be the Lords Souldiers, to fight againſt Satan, World, Fleſh. Beg the Graces and priviledges ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited and ſealed in that ordinance, <hi>Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, Adoption, Mortification, Union to Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 3.5. Rom. 6.1, 2. Gal. 3.26. Act. 22.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Remiſſion of Sin:</hi> ſay, Lord didſt thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe before I could ask them, and now wilt thou not beſtow them, when I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an humble ſuitor for them? I here produce thy Charter, the deed of gift under thine own hand: thou didſt in thy infancy confer a right, give me now poſſeſſion of it, let me know the Seed was ſown by the crop
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:108774:40"/> growing up, that I may at laſt reap the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Harveſt. 2. Repent for your breach of Covenant, alas I have not walkt up to my vow in Baptiſm: I have failed by omiſſion, trangreſſed by commiſſion, my Conſcience condemns me, God may juſtly cenſure me for tranſgreſſing his Laws,<note place="margin">Iſa. 24.5.</note> changing his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, breaking the everlaſting Covenants I have abuſed his kindneſs, rejected his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious offers, neglected his Worſhip, and God may juſtly draw up a black bill of indictment againſt me, paſs the Sentence upon me, and execute it as againſt an Apoſtate, but <hi>Lord heal my back ſlidings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.4.</note> 
                  <hi>love me freely, turn away thine anger from me:</hi> and deal with me accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the tenour of this New Covenant. 3. Plead your Fathers Covenant, Prayers, Practice: <hi>The Lord our God be with us as he was with our Fathers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Kin. 8.57.</note> 
                  <hi>let him not leave us nor forſake us.</hi> Pſal. 22.4, 5. our Fathers truſted in thee, they truſted, and thou didſt deliver them, they cried unto thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> bleſſed be God, the God of my Fathers, that gave them a believing, praying heart; and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſig experiences of anſwers of Prayer: I will build on that Foundation, and ſurely my Lord will not be worſe to me than he was to them; How ſtrong a plea this hath been accounted, ſee in <hi>David,</hi> 1 Chron. 12.17. <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> 2 Chron. 20.6. thus may you plead, Lord, my Godly Father was in many ſtraits, and ſtill he made thee his only refuge and thou didſt not leave him, Oh cut not off this bleſſed entail from me his Child, be
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:108774:40"/> as good to me as thou waſt to him. 4. Walk in the ſteps of your godly Anceſtors, plead and practiſe as they did, ſay as <hi>Moſes,</hi> Exod. 15.2. <hi>He is my God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Kin. 21.3, 4. Pro. 27.10.</note> 
                  <hi>and I will prepare him an habitation; my Fathers God, and I will exalt him:</hi> God <hi>forbid</hi> that I ſhould ſell <hi>the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of my Fathers: My Fathers Friend I will not forſake,</hi> by ſinning or apoſtatiſing, he never gave me occaſion to withdraw from him,<note place="margin">Jer. 2.5.</note> 
                  <hi>What iniquity have my Fathers found in God?</hi> Shall I diſoblige an old Friend, to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie an inveterate Enemy? No God forbid,<note place="margin">Act. 24.14.</note> I will own, love, and ſerve <hi>the God of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> for ever: the God of my Fathers help me to ſtick cloſe to my dear Lord in duty.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This Doctrine concerns perſons that are married, that yet have no Children to Pray and Care for, or incourage themſelves about for ſurviving Poſterity, and under this head I ſhall alſo rank unmarried perſons: both theſe may learn theſe four practical leſſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Be ſure you lay hold of this Covenant for your own Souls: Be concerned for your ſelves; if you have none elſe to care for, yet you have a great charge upon your hands: You are either Gods or Devils to your ſelves; <hi>(aut Deus aut Demon)</hi> either God or Satan is with us, even when alone: Yea every man is the worſt Devil to himſelf <hi>(quiſque ſibi Satan) every man is tempted when he is drawn away of his own luſt and enticed:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jam. 1.14.</note> Your buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is therefore to ſecure your beſt intereſt, whether you ſhall have Children or no: and the only courſe is to lay hold on this
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:108774:41"/> Goſpel-Covenant, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.4, 5. <hi>For thus ſaith the Lord unto the Eunuchs that keep my Sabbaths, and chuſe the thing that pleaſe me, and take hold of my Covenant: Even unto them will I give in my Houſe, and within my Walls a place and a name better than of Sons and of Daughters</hi>—Mark it, you both ſecure your own Souls and your name: How much is this better than <hi>Abſoloms</hi> Pillar, which became an Eternal ſhame? You conſult honour to your ſelves by embracing Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant terms, practiſing Covenant-duties, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving Covenant-promiſes; and Spiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizing Covenant-ſeals, believing in Chriſt the Mediator of the Covenant, being ſprinkled with the blood of the Covenant that you may enjoy Covenant-priviledges; then ſhall your names be inrolled in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Calendar,<note place="margin">Iſa. 4.3.</note> and <hi>written among the living in</hi> Jeruſalem: God and good men will eſteem and honour you, yea, your name ſhall be had in everlaſting remembrance: Your <hi>memory</hi> ſhall be bleſſed on Earth,<note place="margin">Prov. 10.7.</note> and your Souls happy in Heaven: Oh how much is this better than Sons to bear up your name? That's but a Temporal this a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual mercy, that Common to all, this pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to Saints, that uncertain, this fixed, that Temporary this Eternal: Be ſure of this and you are happy.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Be humble and mortified: You want Children, they are an Earthly bleſſing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.<note place="margin">Pſal. 128.3, 4.</note> 3, 4, 5. <hi>For Children are the heritage of the Lord and the fruit of the Womb is his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:108774:41"/> as arrows are in the hands of a mighty man, ſo are the children of Youth, happy is the man that hath his quiver full of them:</hi> Theſe are not contemptible (though temporal) mercies, you muſt not throw up the head, and ſay tuſh, I care not; I have more eaſe and draw a light harrow, I may take my pleaſure, and make even with my Eſtate; for I have none to leave it to when I dye: This is naughtily ſpoken, God would have you humbled under the want of Children, tho' but a temporal mercy: Gods Servants have lookt on it as an Affliction: You may here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by take occaſion to exerciſe Repentance, and enquire what ſin he is now puniſhing you for; thus you may make a virtue of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity: Your defect of Children may prove an increaſe of your graces: But take heed of deſpiſing the bleſſing, or taking occaſion of revelling away your Eſtates; that's an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream one way, as penuriouſneſs is unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in you on the other hand, both are ſins to be avoided, and mortified, ſtudy, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Mortifie therefore your members which are upon the Earth, Fornication, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, Inordinate Affection, Evil Concupiſence, and Covetouſneſs which is Idolatry.</hi> Away with all licentious practiſes; live Chaſtly, modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, moderately, humbly, diligently in both callings.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Adopt ſome to be a Child or Children to you, if you be perſons of any Eſtates: this is Mr. <hi>Paul Bains</hi> advice: <q>they muſt, ſaith he, not revel with their Subſtance, nor
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:108774:42"/> muſt they live like idle perſons and buſy-bodies for want of this imployment, but they muſt ſave the matter of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and depute ſome as Adopted Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and be helpful in Educating others.</q> Thus he: Adoption hath been uſed in all civilized nations, and it is <hi>In alienam famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am tranſitus,</hi> A paſſing legally out of one Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily into another: And amongſt the Romans it was <hi>[Aut per praetorium, aut per populum:]</hi> That which was done by the Proetors was called Adoption; That which was done by the People was called Arrogation. They had many formalities about it, needleſs here to be recounted. But by this means you may have children whom you may account as your own: you rich men, that God hath denied the fruit of your bodies to, have you no near kinſmen, or poor neighbours, to whom God hath granted a lovely off-ſpring? ſurely it would be acceptable both to God, them, and your ſelves, to pick out an inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous child, help him to learning; train him up for God; bequeath your Eſtates to make an Experiment of him while you live; So may you have comfort of him, and he may bear up your name: Do good with your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and be ſerviceable in Church and Commonwealth. I know ſome rich men grudg and envy any that are likely to enter into their labours: but as <hi>their glory will not deſcend after them,</hi> ſo uſually thoſe Eſtates do no good when they are gone;<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.17. Eccl. 2.19.</note> 
                  <hi>For who knoweth whether he ſhall be a wiſe man or a fool, that ſhall have rule over his labour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:108774:42"/>4. Take more time and pains for the good of your own Souls, and lay out your ſelves for the good of others: if you be unmarried ſtudy that Text: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.33, 35. <hi>He that is unmarried careth for the things that belong to the Lord,</hi> how he may pleaſe the Lord. Not that married perſons have a <hi>Superſedeas,</hi> or <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> from Soul-concerns. But the un-married have a more leiſure and fairer opportunity for immediate acts of Devotion. Married perſons have ſome divertiſements (in themſelves lawful) which un-married are free from. The Married may have nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Children, and ſo have many diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which Childleſs perſons are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled in; and ſo may <hi>[Vacare Deo]</hi> be more at leiſure for God; or as the word is, <hi>attend on the Lord without diſtraction.</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,] ſit cloſe to the Lord without Disjunction; <hi>[Indiviſâ cum domino conjunctione vivatur]</hi> like the faithful ſervants who depart not from their Maſters ſide: O happy ſouls who have an heart and leiſure to keep ſo cloſe to God! You have more time than others, ſee your feet and hands and heart run parallel: Your oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities are double to others. Let your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement be doubled. You have no chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to lay up for: Lay out the more for God. He expects more from you than from others. You have no children to maintain; <hi>Honour the Lord with your ſubſtance.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 3.9.</note> Buy Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Catechiſms for poor Children. Maintain them at School. Relieve the poor.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:108774:43"/> Incourage a Goſpel Miniſtry. Give the tenth part at leaſt of your yearly incomes to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Uſes. Let your own hands be your Executors. Truſt not others when you are dead; For as it is no thanks to you to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath Legacies when you are forced to leave all, ſo you know not how they will be imbezelled or disburſed. Beſides, you loſe the opportunity of ſhewing your chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Diſpoſition. Living Springs ſend forth ſtreams liberally. Dead Pits afford nothing but what is drawn out with Buckets. Watch and catch at Objects and occaſions of doing good. Spare upon your ſelves, but be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral in good uſes, Let your Superfluities give way to your Brothers Conveniencies: Your Conveniencies to his Neceſſities: Yea, your Neceſſities muſt go to ſupply his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities. Fear not wanting your ſelves: You put all into a good Bank. Dare you not truſt God upon his Bills of Return, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes? If you lend to the Lord, doubtleſs he will repay: Do you fear the Alſufficient God will turn Bankrupt? Conſult the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences of Gods ſervants, and ſee if the Jewiſh Proverb have not proved true, <hi>[De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cima ut dives fias]</hi> Pay Tythes that thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt be rich. Remember what our Lord ſaith, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.38. <hi>Give, and it ſhall be given you, good meaſure, preſſed down, ſhaken together, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning over, ſhall men give into your boſomes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:108774:43"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> An Exhortation to Parents, to have their Children within the bleſſed Covenant.</head>
               <p>I Have diſpatched the three firſt Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. 4. The laſt concerns all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to do their endeavour to the uttermoſt to bring their Children, and leave them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Covenant. Alas! What ſignifies your leaving them great Eſtates, Hundreds a Year, or Thouſands of Gold and Silver, in compariſon of this? <hi>David</hi> was a King, and his many Sons Noble Princes, and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> one of the moſt glorious Monarchs that ever the Sun ſaw: ſo that it became a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>Solomon in all his glory.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Mat. 6.29. 2 Chro. 11.15.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Laurence Saunder</hi> writ to his Wife, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches I have none to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow you with, but that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, How ſweet Chriſt is, which I feel, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath to you. <hi>Fox Mon.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> And <hi>David</hi> left him in peaceable poſſeſſion of the Kingdom, <hi>and the Lord magnified him exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly:</hi> Yet all this did not cheer up dying <hi>Davids</hi> heart ſo much as this bleſſed Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. That's but a carnal heart that can brag of what treaſures of worldly riches he leaves his children. The gracious ſoul would rather bequeath a promiſe to them, than all the wealth of the Indies. <hi>Zenophon</hi> tells us, that one being asked, Where's your Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? He anſwered him [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,] Where <hi>Cyrus</hi> my friend is: Much more may a Chriſtian ſay, Chriſt is my Friend, and my All. Oh that I could leave him in the boſom of my dear Child! That is the height
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:108774:44"/> of my Ambition, to have my Children gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and glorified. As an honeſt Miniſter ſaid, If I may but ſee the fear of God in my Children, <hi>[Satis habeo, ſatiſque mihi, uxori, filiis &amp; filiabus perſpexi.]</hi> I have enough, and my ſelf, Wife, Sons, Daughters, are all well provided for; I need no more. Oh! that God would ſet Parents hearts towards the Covenant of God! I ſhall give ſome Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives and Directions. 1. For Motives, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you conſider:</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 23.</note>1. That your Children are <hi>Children of wrath, as well as others:</hi> You begot them as Men, not as Holy Men, for Grace was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventitious. <hi>Adam</hi> begot a Son <hi>in his own likeneſs,<note place="margin">Gen. 5.3.</note> after his own Image,</hi> not Gods, which he had loſt. For Grace comes by ſpiritual regeneration, not by natural generation: You gave them a ſinful and miſerable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing! O ſtudy to give them an holy and happy being. They are born in ſin; <hi>Travel over them till Chriſt be formed in them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 4.19.</note> If you cannot make them good, yet lament that they are ſo bad: You have done them a diſ-kindneſs: Labour to do them this kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to plant Grace in them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Your Children are more inclined to Vice than Vertue; they are born <hi>like the wild Aſſes Colt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 11.12.</note> with a byas Hell-wards, and an antipathy in their nature to what is good: For <hi>the carnal mind is enmity againſt good:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Aelian</hi> tells of a Whore, that boaſted ſhe could eaſily get Scholars away from <hi>Socrates,</hi> but <hi>Socrates</hi> could get no Schollars from her.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:108774:44"/> Wrong is always before right; naturally, the left hand before the right. Children need not be taught what is bad, they learn that faſt enough: but you'll find much ado to beat into them what is good.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Yet they muſt learn Divine Truths, and their Duty, or never be happy. <hi>One thing is needfull;</hi> If they die as they are born,<note place="margin">Luke 10.4.</note> with their backs on God, they are undone for ever; they are become like the beaſts that periſh. But it's better be a beaſt,<note place="margin">Eccl. 3.2.</note> than to be a rational man like a beaſt; The one goeth upwards to be judged by God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to eternal torments; but the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive ſpirit of a beaſt goeth downwards to the Earth: And however ſome think the Beaſt ſhall not loſe its individuation, yet it is not capable of Moral Evil, and ſo of the Puniſhment of Hell, as a rational, but a grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſoul is. Would you not have them far worſe than Beaſts? Oh! take pains to work grace in them, elſe no ſalvation, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.3.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They are capable of Inſtruction. For this end was the Book of Proverbs written,<note place="margin">Prov. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>To give ſubtilty to the ſimple, to the young man know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and diſcretion. Ariſtotle</hi> indeed ſaith, That a young man is not a fit hearer of Moral Philoſophy, or of Ethicks; but he ſpeaks of what is, <hi>[De facto, non de eo quod fieri debet,]</hi> what is uſually, not what ought to be. Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren can learn Trades, Toys, why not Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Catichiſms? It's not enough to tell the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of many Children: were they Idiots, or Natural Fools, deſtitute of Common Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:108774:45"/> it were a lamentable judgment of God, and a ſore affliction to Parents. But they have members of Body, uſe of Reaſon. Oh! do what you can to add Grace. You are taken with their outward Feature, wit, Parts; theſe qualifie them not for Heaven, till Gods Image be ſuper-induced.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Parents have great advantage in begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with their Children, whilſt young: Now they are young and tender, ſooneſt reduced. Like young twigs quickly bended, or a young Horſe eaſily broken, or a young Hawk ſooneſt brought to the lure. Take them betimes, before they be hardened in ſin, and you may moſt likely prevail; but if they be let alone awhile, they'll be paſt deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with. Cuſtom in ſin makes them like the <hi>Aethiopian in his skin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 13.23.</note> 
                  <hi>or the Leopard ſpots.</hi> Beſides, teach them betimes, and they will more likely retain it. It is an uſual ſaying, <hi>[Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quidae ſunt puerorum memoriae,<note place="margin">Quo ſemel eſt imbuta recens ſervabit odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remteſta diu-</note>]</hi> Childrens me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories are ſoft, and ſooneſt take impreſſion, and clear or free from diſturbance, and ſo retain it longeſt. Seaſon a New Veſſel, and it will keep that favour long: Let Cloath be died in Wooll, and after in Cloath, the colour will be moſt lively and durable. The Application is eaſie.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Parents are betruſted with their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Souls as well as Bodies:<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.4.</note> 
                  <hi>All Souls are mine,</hi> ſaith God, and he concredits them to the tuition of Parents as a precious Talent, or depoſitum, ſaying as <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s Daughter to <hi>Moſes</hi> Mother,<note place="margin">Exod. 2.9.</note> 
                  <hi>take this child away, and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:108774:45"/> nurſe it for me, and I will give thee thy Wages:</hi> ſo ſaith God (when the Child is Born and Baptized) to Parents, I devolve the charge of this child on thee, look to it,<note place="margin">Ezek. 3.17.</note> if it miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry through thy default, its blood will I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire at thy hand: thou muſt give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of its Soul: go then to God and ſay as <hi>Manoah</hi> concerning his Son <hi>Sampſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judges 13.12.</note> 
                  <hi>how ſhall we order the Child? And how ſhall we do unto him?</hi> Fetch your inſtructions from God, and aſſiſtance alſo for your Childrens good, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of a reckoning day.</p>
               <p n="7">7. By this you will manifeſt your own ſincerity or ſiniſterity, your love to God and your Children, or your hatred; Remember, no man is really good that is not Relatively good: <hi>When thou art converted ſtrengthen thy Brethren,</hi> ſaith our Lord, <hi>i. e.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 22.32.</note> evidence the ſincerity of thy converſion, by endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring the good of others: Grace is like Fire that turns what it toucheth into its own nature: if you do not your endeavour to bring others, (eſpecially your ſeed) into co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, it's a ſhrewd ſign you are not your ſelves in Covenant with God: then wo be to you, Oh curſed Parents of curſed Children! Are you ſo indifferent whether Chriſts Kingdom be reared and erected in your Family, that you'll ſcarce put up a prayer, or ſpeak a word to promote it? Where is your love to Chriſt that loved Souls ſo dearly? And where is your true love to your natural off-ſpring? if a Beaſt be fallen in a Pit, will you not help him out? Haſt
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:108774:46"/> thou more care of a Swine than the Soul of thy Child?</p>
               <p n="8">8. Satan lyes at the catch for your Children, that Fiend of Hell hunteth daily for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soul of thy dear Child: he got poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion when thy Child came into the World, and he makes it his buſineſs to keep poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and will do till Chriſt that's <hi>ſtronger than he</hi> caſt him out:<note place="margin">Luk. 11.22.</note> and wilt thou ſee a Dog, a Bear, the Lion of Hell hurry away thy Child, Man, and not cry out to Heaven for aid? O heard-hearted miſcreant! doth not nature teach the Hen to fly at the glade that would take her Chickens; yea the Sheep to turn upon the Dog that would catch her Lamb? And art thou ſo far degenerated as to caſt of all pity to thine own bowels? Oh Monſter of Mankind! haſt thou laid aſide Humanity, as well as Chriſtianity?</p>
               <p n="9">9. The Church and Commonwealth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire this office of love from you to your Children: and if you neglect their Education you take a courſe to corrupt both. It's worth obſerving, that the Heathen Romans ſued in their Courts of Judicature, ſuch perſons as were not careful in Educating their Children; <hi>Cicero</hi> laid this to the charge of <hi>Verres,</hi> that he had debauched his Son, by Intemperance, Riot, Wantonneſs; it ſeems it was actiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble among Heathens, and it were well if it were puniſhed among pretended Chriſtians; Wo be to that Town where the Springs are poiſoned: ſad is the caſe of that Church and State where Academies and Inns of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:108774:46"/> Court are corrupted, yea, <hi>corrupters;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 1.4. Hoſ. 5.7.</note> where <hi>ſtrange Children are begot</hi> and brought up; no reformation can be expected till publick Schools be reformed. It's ſaid of <hi>Protagoras</hi> he lived 60 years, and ſpent 40 years in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting youth; if not only Old Trees in an Orchard be rotten but young alſo, what fruit can be expected? Its fit they be digged up, by this we may Divine what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of a Church or Kingdom.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The conſequence is ſad of Parents neglect of their Childrens due education: <hi>a Child left to himſelf bringeth his Mother to ſhame,</hi> Pro. 29.15. throw the Reines on the Childs Neck, and whither will he not run? <hi>A fooliſh Son is the heavinéſs of his Mother,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 10.1. Pro. 19.15. Pro. 17.21.</note> the calamity of his Father: neither Father nor Mother have joy in a wicked Child, and uſually they may thank themſelves for it; the Switzers had a law, that if a Child was condemned to dye, the Parent ſhould exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute him, becauſe it's neglect in Parents that is uſually the rack of their Children: it's true a godly Man may have a bad Son, but this is moſt ordinary. Oh what ſhame will co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Face, and horrour fill the Conſcience of a bad Father, or a good Father conſcious of guilt, when he ſhall ſee his Child running hell-wards, or roaring in thoſe unquenchable Torments! I adviſe you therefore to a time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly care to prevent theſe dreadful conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What courſe ſhould Parents take to reſtrain ſin in Children, principle them
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:108774:47"/> with Grace, and bring them within the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of God?</p>
               <p>I anſwer this is a large and ordinary ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that I cannot now inſiſt on: practical Divines lay four great duties before Parents, for the Education of their Children,
<list>
                     <item>1. Proviſion.</item>
                     <item>2. Correction.</item>
                     <item>3. Inſtruction.</item>
                     <item>4. Prayer, Supplication.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Providing Food, Rayment, a Calling: This though a great duty, I paſs, as not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to our caſe: only I find this remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able paſſage, that the Athenians ordered in their laws, that if Parents had not brought up their Children in a lawful calling, they ſhould not be bound to keep their Parents: thus all were ſet to Trades.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For correction, I ſhall not inlarge on that, only obſerve it to be done ſeaſonably, Prov. 19.18, <hi>Chaſten thy Son while there is hope,</hi> ſome put it off till he become too ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, do it with ſelf-reflection, humiliation, moderation, prayer, inſtructing them in their fault, and the way to mend it. I paſs this alſo.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Inſtruction, this I chiefly aimed at, if I had leaſure, an hint of 1. The Matter. 2. The Manner of performing this duty.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For Matter, inſtruct your Children in the main fundamental principles of our Chriſtian Religion, as, that there is a God; concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, his nature, properties, perſons of the God-head: the creation of the World; of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:108774:47"/> Man, the Immortality of the Soul; the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Sin; the fall of <hi>Adam;</hi> the ſad fruits thereof: the Remedy by Chriſt, his Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation Offices, Exaltation; the Duty of Man; the nature of a Church; priviledges, proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Believers; the Ordinances, the ſtate of all men after death; Rewards and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You are likewiſe to inſtruct them in the Covenant of Grace; the nature, uſe, ends of it; the difference betwixt this and the old Covenant of Works; the Mediator of it; the terms, properties, and conditions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; the ſeals of it. Baptiſm and the Lords Supper; the priviledge and neceſſity of Souls being within it: preſs them with Arguments to enter into it, give directions about it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the Manner of your inſtructing your Children, you muſt do it. 1.<note place="margin">Iſa. 28.9.</note> Timouſly as ſoon as they are capable, but <hi>drawn from the breaſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.15.</note> 
                  <hi>[ab incunabulis]</hi> that they may ſuck in knowledge with there mothers milk as <hi>Timothy.</hi> 2. Frequently, once is not enough but you muſt inculcate truths on them, whet them, as you go oft with the Knife upon the Whet-ſtone,<note place="margin">Deut. 6.7.</note> ſo the word ſignifies. 3. Experimentally not by rote, hear-ſay, work things on your hearts,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.21.</note> learn and ſpeak the truth <hi>as it is in Jeſus:</hi> ſpeak feelingly, from the Heart, as one that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves thy ſelf. 4. Wiſely,<note place="margin">Jud. 22.23. Col. 3.21.</note> obſerve the tempers of your Children, ſome muſt be drawn, others driven, provoke not tender-hearted to fretting, diſcontent. 5. Seaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:108774:48"/> obſerve <hi>[candida tempora]</hi> proper melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeaſons,<note place="margin">Eccl. 8.5. Pſa. 14.10.</note> as a good humour, affliction, conviction, ſpeak to them words upon the Wheel, or in ſome nick of time, when they will be beſt taken. 6. Lovingly, winningly, meekly, not in paſſion, but draw with cords of love:<note place="margin">Hoſ. 11.3.</note> oil them with kindneſs, and they will go down glibly: even bitter Pills rolled in Sugar will be well taken. 7. Plainly, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly, not in high flown language, but uſe ſimilitudes, ſpeak as they are able to bear it,<note place="margin">Iſa. 28.10, 11.</note> come on gradually, <hi>[guttatim]</hi> by drops, here a little there a little, into theſe narrow mouth'd veſſels. 8. Faithfully, ſearch the wound, do not skin it over: a fair hand makes a foul wound:<note place="margin">Luk. 19.22.</note> a weak doſe rather ſtirs, than purgeth out bad humours, rebuke ſharply.<note place="margin">Tit. 1.14.</note> 9. Scripturally, bring your autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity along with you ſhew them chapter and verſe,<note place="margin">Act. 18.24, 28.</note> Gods authority joined with yours may prevail much,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cor. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 5.</note> theſe are Spiritual Weapons. 10.<note place="margin">Rom. 10.1.</note> Prayingly, pray ſolemnly before an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, by Ejaculation, in ſpeaking: it's not your work but Gods to make it ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: Be ſenſible that all is loſt if God give it not the ſetting on, and ſtrike with the great hammer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:108774:48"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Directions to Parents, and encouragements in their pleading for their Children.</head>
               <p n="4">4. THE laſt Exhortation to Parents on the behalf of their ſurviving Children is prayer and ſupplication, this is a natural du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and catholick relief to the aking hearts of Godly Parents, not only to obtain Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as <hi>Hanna,</hi> but for Grace in Children, when they go aſtray: hence it was that holy <hi>Abraham,</hi> to whom this Covenant was firſt made, breaths out his longing Soul in a ſhort Ejaculation for his wild Son, <hi>Oh that</hi> Iſhmael <hi>might live before thee!</hi> Gen. 17.18. <hi>q. d.</hi> I thank God for <hi>Iſaac,</hi> but I am not ſatisfied with <hi>Iſaac</hi> only, I muſt beg Spiritual and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life for my extravagant Son <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> though he be not the Son of the Promiſe: yet let him be a Son of Promiſe; if <hi>Iſaac</hi> muſt have the Earthly <hi>Canaan,</hi> let not <hi>Iſhmael</hi> be excluded out of the heavenly. Thus muſt you plead with the Lord for Children.</p>
               <p>To aſſiſt you herein, I ſhall ſubjoyn ſome pleas, Arguments and Encouragements not to move God, but to quicken your Faith, Hope, and Importunity. Thus then ſay.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Lord, this Covenant thou haſt made with Believers and their Seed, did ſpring only from the Fountain of thy Free-grace: this Promiſe commenced before I had a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:108774:49"/> and therefore could not depend on any worthineſs in me;<note place="margin">Deut. 7.7, 8.</note> the Lord did not ſet his love on Iſrael becauſe they were better than others, but becauſe he loved them, the love of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevolence produced the love of complacency, it's an <hi>Everlaſting love</hi> both in its original and duration:<note place="margin">Jer. 31.3.</note> it hath no cauſe but in Gods breaſt, and ſhall have no end: Lord, for thy words ſake,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.21. compared with 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 17.19.</note> yea, <hi>for thy Servants ſake,</hi> [<hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt, who is Gods Eſſential word] and according to thy own heart, haſt thou done all theſe great things: hadſt thou ſeen any ſtop or obſtruction on my part, thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt have forborn making this Covenant. But ſuch a Covenant there is, and Grace made it, look into thine own heart, Lord, and as Grace only made it, ſo let Grace perform it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Lord, Thou art true and faithful in the performance of thy promiſes: <hi>Mercy</hi> made this Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mic. 7.20. Numb. 23.19. Pſal. 89.35.</note> 
                  <hi>Truth</hi> performs it to <hi>Jacob:</hi> thou art not as man that thou ſhouldſt lye; thou haſt ſworn by <hi>thy holineſs</hi> that thou wilt not <hi>lye unto David:</hi> well Lord, in hopes of the performance of thy Covenant, I married, begot Children, gave them up to God in Baptiſm, wherein thou tookeſt them as thine own; and doſt thou now repent of thy choice? Oh no, thou haſt told me in thy word,<note place="margin">Iſa. 54.9, 10.</note> that thy Covenant-promiſes are as ſure as the Waters of <hi>Noah</hi> not overflowing the World:<note place="margin">Jer. 31.35, 36, 37.</note> yea the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Hills will ſooner depart, than God go back from his word: yea his Covenant
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:108774:49"/> is as ſure as the Ordinances of Heaven, Sun Moon and Stars: as ſure as day and night; Lord, my Soul having got ſuch good hold of thee by Faith, I will not let go this hold, but ſtick faſt till thou make good thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to me and my ſeed: I am reſolved to ſue thy Bond, by Faith and Prayer, till thou pay this debt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Lord, thou haſt made this Covenant good to others: thou haſt performed the mercy promiſed to our Fathers, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred thy holy Covenant:<note place="margin">Luk. 1.45, 55, 72.</note> there hath been a performance of the things ſpoken by the Lord: never could any ſtand forth, and chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge thee for the breach of promiſe, from the beginning of the World to this day: and I humbly hope thou wilt not begin with me:<note place="margin">Gen. 13.16, 17, 18.</note> thou madeſt a promiſe to <hi>Abraham</hi> of a numerous off-ſpring and inhabiting <hi>Canaan,</hi> and thou didſt perform all to a tittle, yea to a minute, the leaſt Iota did not fail, or fall to the ground: and thou art as great, as good, as powerful, as merciful now as ever;<note place="margin">Gen. 18.14. Job 42.2.</note> thou ſayeſt, <hi>is any thing too hard for the Lord?</hi> My Soul Eccho's, No: I know, that thou canſt do every thing: with God all things are poſſible, <hi>I believe, Lord, help my unbelief;</hi> thou art able to reduce my Prodigal Child, to convert my ſtubborn Child: Oh give a proof of thy power in this great work.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Lord, thou haſt made good the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to my own Soul: my Parents improved and pleaded thy Covenant for me, a ſinful wretch, and wilt thou not make the ſame
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:108774:50"/> good to mine? I muſt ſay as once <hi>Solomon, Thou haſt kept with thy Servant</hi> David <hi>my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Kin. 8.23, 24.</note> 
                  <hi>that thou promiſedſt him, thou ſpakeſt alſo with thy Mouth, and haſt fulfilled it with thy hand, as it is this day:</hi> Bleſſed be the God of my Fathers, that hath not cut off his kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from me, that am the Seed of thoſe faithful ones, that are now at reſt with thee: I my ſelf, can riſe up and bear witneſs to thy faithfulneſs <hi>[Ecce ſignum]</hi> Behold a teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Divine love:<note place="margin">Pſal. 86.16, 17.</note> thou haſt <hi>ſhewed me a token for good,</hi> who am <hi>the Son of thy handmaid:</hi> and I take this as a pledge of more kindneſs to mine:<note place="margin">Pſal. 116.16.</note> thou haſt looſed my Bonds, wilt thou not alſo knock off the Fetters of ſin from my poor Child? I was as wicked as any; and coſt my Father, and Mother many a tear and groan, but thou heardeſt their Prayer, wilt thou not alſo hear me?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Lord; I do find all that I want for my ſelf and ſeed within the compaſs of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: for as thou haſt promiſed to be my God, and pardon ſin, ſo thou haſt underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to work the conditions thou requireſt, as abſolutely neceſſary for obtaining the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of the Covenant: thou ſay'ſt <hi>they ſhall all know me from the leaſt to the greateſt of them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 31.34.</note> 
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> as I underſtand it, young as well as old:<note place="margin">Deut. 30.6.</note> thou ſayſt, <hi>the Lord thy God will circumciſe thy heart, and the heart of thy Seed, to love the Lord thy God.</hi> Again thou ſay'ſt, <hi>They that dwell under his ſhadow ſhall return:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.7.</note> amongſt whom are Children: and that <hi>he will turn the hearts of the Fathers with the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 4.6.</note>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:108774:50"/> (ſo ſome read it:) this is enough Lord, may my Children be ſavingly converted, I have all my deſire, for this ſhall be their Salvation; and I have theſe promiſes under thy hand, and ſurely they are not inſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Yea, Lord, thou haſt converted ſome whoſe immediate Parents were not in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and whether their remote Parents, were ſo, who can tell? I plainly diſcern thou ſometimes leapeſt out of the ordinary road, reaching over the heads of ſome near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier related, to lay hold on ſtrangers hearts, and I do not grudge them this mercy, but adore the freeneſs of Divine Grace: only, my Soul fetcheth ſome encouragement thence,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.17, 23. Hoſ. 2.23.</note> will my Lord <hi>graft into the true Olive</hi> ſome <hi>wild branches,</hi> and not take in natural? Wilt thou ſay, <hi>Ammi my people</hi> to them that were not thy people, and wilt thou ſay <hi>Lo ammi</hi> to ſuch as cling to thee, are reſolved not to forgo thee? Oh my Lord, the exuberancy of Free-grace to ſtrangers is an incouragement to me; and thus I ſay, will my Father give ſuch lumps of bread to Dogs, and can he not afford a crum to a Child? I ſee ſome, whoſe Parents never ſpake a word to God for them, eminent in Grace, and Monuments of free-grace, and ſhall any of my Children, which thou haſt taken into thy Family be ſhut out of thy doors? I hope not.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Lord, if thou hadſt a deſign to deny my ſuit thou wouldſt have ſhut my mouth in prayer: for thy word ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 10.17</note> 
                  <hi>Thou wilt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:108774:51"/> their heart, thou wilt cauſe thine ear to hear:</hi> An inlarged heart in Prayer, is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a mean, but a pledge of gracious audience: ſurely thou wilt not ſend thy Spirit into my heart, and draw out my heart to thee in vain: when a Father bids his Child ask, he deſigns to give: thou wilt not let this bleſſed ſpirit breathe in vain in my ſoul. Wilt thou inlarge my heart, and not grant my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt?<note place="margin">Pſal. 38.9.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord, all my deſire is before thee, and my groaning is not hid from thee.</hi> In thee, O Lord, do I hope, thou wilt hear me, O Lord, my God. Thou haſt raiſed my heart in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, wilt thou not give me the mercy I expect?</p>
               <p n="8">8. Lord, is not thy Glory concerned in this affair as well as my comfort? And yet my comfort is ſomething in thine eye; For thou ſayſt,<note place="margin">Pſ. 118.15.</note> 
                  <hi>The voyce of rejoycing and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is in the Tabernacles of the righteous:</hi> And alas! What joy can there be in a family, when a <hi>fooliſh Son</hi> is <hi>heavineſs</hi> both to Father and Mother,<note place="margin">Prov. 10.1.</note> and a diſturbance to the whole houſe? But oh! thy Name is diſhonoured by my own fleſh; wicked men hardened; ſome ſcandalized by the miſcarrying of the Children of the Covenant. But on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand, if Covenant-grace be ſpread up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my childs heart, by Converting-grace, many will <hi>glorifie God:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 1.24.</note> His own Soul will be the actual lively Trumpet of Divine Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by confeſſing ſin, and turning to God; thy Omniſcience, Grace and Omnipotency, will be made glorious; And who can tell
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:108774:51"/> how many may be won to God by his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2 Theſ. 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and every Convert <hi>Glorifies God in the day of their viſitation,</hi> and at the great Day God will be <hi>glorified in his Saints.</hi> Lord, conſult thy Glory!</p>
               <p n="9">9. Lord, thou haſt given me ſome incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement concerning this Child I am pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for: When my Child was young he was very hopeful; now he is grown up, my hopes are daſht: He hath now embraced the world, or is fallen into bad company and courſes: the leſs are my hopes now, becauſe he is a woful Apoſtate, and ſins againſt more light than others, and this daunts and damps my ſpirit: however I will pray and wait ſtill, for what is a daunting to me,<note place="margin">Gen. 22.14.</note> is rather an advantage to thee. <hi>In the mount of the Lord it is ſeen.</hi> When the knife is at <hi>Iſaac's</hi> throat,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.14.</note> the <hi>valley of Achor</hi> is a <hi>door of hope.</hi> When men ſay, <hi>our bones are dryed, our hope is lost,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezeck. 37.11, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>we are cut off for our parts,</hi> then <hi>the graves are opened,</hi> and there's life from the dead. The caſe is mine. I am ſaying as <hi>Jonah, I am caſt out of his ſight:</hi> yet will I look again toward thy holy Temple. The other look may fetch the mercy. There's a may be in the caſe: Can a Child of ſo many Prayers and Fears miſcarry?</p>
               <p>This brings to mind a paſſage in <hi>Melchior Adamus, De vitis Theol. Germ. pag.</hi> 724. It is this; The mother of <hi>Hunnius,</hi> being with child of him, had a Viſion; She thought ſhe was in the Church, and took up a Reed, or a Straw, or ſuch a ſmall thing; While ſhe
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:108774:52"/> held it in her Fingers, it ſo increaſed, that ſhe was almoſt oppreſſed with its weight, even to death. She preſently ſaw it turned into a Pillar of the Temple; Then ſhe was eaſed of her burden. This was verified in her Son <hi>Hunnius,</hi> who though religiouſly edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, and hopeful in Childhood, yet fell into bad Company, and then into horrible Temptations, and ſad Apprehenſions, That he had committed the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, but by Grace was recovered, and proves an excellent inſtrument in the Church of God. This may be of uſe to poor affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted deſponding Parents.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Lord, If thou deny my ſuit, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie thy Juſtice, in the rejection and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of My child; I muſt and will acquieſce in thy Soveraign righteous Will. It's hard to bring my heart to it, but I will ſay, Thy Will be done.<note place="margin">Rom. 11.33</note> 
                  <hi>Oh the depth of the riches both of the wiſdom and knowledg of God! How un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable are thy judgments, and thy ways paſt finding out?</hi> I my ſelf deſerve to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken and caſt into Hell. I have many a time told thee, I muſt for ever juſtifie God with flames about mine ears, if thy juſtice be glorified in my deſtruction for all my abominations: And if thou deal thus with my beloved Off ſpring, I will ſay, <hi>The Lord is righteous in all his wayes, and holy in all his works.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 9.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> belongeth unto thee, but unto me and mine <hi>confuſion of faces.</hi> I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my all to thee, and thank thee for grace in my own ſoul, and hopes of Glory; and if
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:108774:52"/> my wilful child may not bring a revenue of Glory to free Grace, I will be content with thy raiſing up a revenue of Glory to thy Juſtice in his juſt condemnation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But what tender-hearted Parent can be contented to ſee his Child damned!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> You muſt diſtinguiſh betwixt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Grace. Nature loves its own, and cannot bear to ſee part of it ſelf in miſery. Yea, grace cannot but deſire, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but earneſtly breathe after the ſpiritual and eternal good of our Children. And 'tis not only lawfull, but duty to deſire it. Yet if God deny it, Grace brings man's Will to a due ſubmiſſion to the Divine diſpoſal; for the more a Chriſtian is like to God, the more is his Will melted into God's Will; and therefore will a Child of God rejoyce in the execution of Gods juſtice upon dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt carnal Relations at the great Day. As ſanctified <hi>Levi</hi> in the cauſe of God,<note place="margin">Deut. 33.9</note> ſaid to his Father and his Mother, <hi>I have not ſeen:</hi> neither did he acknowledg his Brethren, nor knew his own Children. Nature will be in a ſort ſwallowed by grace in Gods good pleaſure. That was a remarkable paſſage of a gracious Gentlewoman that had a vicious Son, who fell into many debaucheries, and into one hainous Act, which ſunk her ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſpirit: But recovering her ſelf, ſhe ſaid to him with ſome warmth, Ah! my ſinful Son, thou haſt coſt me many a Tear, Groan, and bitter hour; but a day is coming, when I ſhall triumph in ſeeing the juſt vengeance
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:108774:53"/> of God excecuted upon thee: this did ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall the young Gentleman that he laid it to heart, repented, and became a new man, to the joy of his Godly Mother: But,</p>
               <p n="2">2. You muſt diſtinguiſh about Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and look on it as under a double notion, 1. as a ſtate of compleat Sinning, Blaſpheming and hating God to the utmoſt. God calls you not to be content with this, which is ſo directly contrary to the Grace of God in the Chriſtian: nor yet may you be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to have your Child ſeparated from God, the cheifeſt good; which is the worſt part of hell. But, 2. Hell may be conſidered as a place or ſtate of torment, and miſery, to the Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Creature: and upon this account, you muſt not be contented ſimply to have your Child tormented, which is abhorent to nature, but your Souls muſt be ſo overr-uled with the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine pleaſure, as where his will is manifeſted, you muſt reſt ſatisfied in that by which God thinks fit to Glorify himſelf.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Yet further, ſay, Lord, if thou refuſe to hear me for this or that particular Child, yet I will thank thee for Free Grace expreſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to another Child, or more of my Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that are-hopefull: God forbid that my ſorrow for our Child ſhould drown all my Comfort in another, or my complaints ſhould ſilence my gratitude: I will praiſe thee for what I enjoy, and hope for more: Nature teacheth perſons to beg a future, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging a former kindneſs. I Bleſs the Lord, I have a Praying, Obeying Child, that
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:108774:53"/> was born as deſtitute of Grace as this: and I humbly take this as a pledg of more; Thou haſt Grace enough for all my Children, I will not deſpond, but be thankfull; ſuch a Child I hope, hath embraced the Covenant of God: <hi>Who am I, O Lord God!</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 7.18, 19, 20.</note> 
                  <hi>and what is my houſe? That thou haſt brought me hitherto. And this was yet a ſmall thing in thy ſight, O Lord God? but thou haſt ſpoken alſo of thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants houſe for a great while to come: and is this the manner of man, O Lord God?</hi> Thou didſt not owe me any thing, and yet thou haſt given me the beſt things: 'Tis true I have a <hi>Cain,</hi> yet I have a Righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> I have a <hi>Shem</hi> as well as a <hi>Cham,</hi> an <hi>Iſaac</hi> as well as an <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> a <hi>Jacob,</hi> as well as an <hi>Eſau,</hi> a <hi>Solomon</hi> as well as an <hi>Ammon,</hi> or <hi>Abſalon:</hi> All my Children were born in Sin, and God might have ſuffered all to have dyed in Sin: But bleſſed be Free-Grace, that hath pluckt this or that as a brand out of the Fire; God hath heard prayers and taken of my Seed, to be the Lords, he hath not dealt ſo with all Families. I own this as an higher preferment for my Children then if they were the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt princes on Earth, I will be thankful for them, yet jealous of them, and mix my praiſes with prayers, the heart is very deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; I will give God Glory, yet not glory in my Children: But my jealouſie ſhall not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure thy Glory of this mercy. <hi>Ebenezer</hi> hitherto God hath helpt. I will rejoyce with trembling: ſomething God hath done that I may love and praiſe him, and be encouraged
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:108774:54"/> to hope for more: Much is yet to do that I may ſtill have an Errand to the Throne of Grace, thus my Lord keeps me in a waiting depending poſture I muſt have ſomething to evidence that God is my God, and an hearer of Prayer: I muſt not have all, that I may know I am on Earth, and not in Heaven: It may be Religion may live in my Family when I am dead and gone: And if all my Seed be not happy, I hope ſome may: However God hath done my own Soul good, and laid a foundation of Grace in my heart, and will lay the top Stone in Glory: It was a notable ſpeech of that gracious Miniſter of Chriſt, One Mr. <hi>Avery,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See the life of <hi>Mr. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> p. 131.</note> paſſing to <hi>New-England,</hi> in a Storm at Sea, expecting every wave to bring death, he lift up his Eyes to Heaven, and Said, Lord I cannot challeng of preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of my life, but according to thy Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant I challeng Heaven: Immediatly a wave waſted him to Heaven: he his Wife, and five Children, being then drowned: and is this nothing that thou may'ſt with gratitude and confidence claim a Promiſe for thy own Salvation: If it reach no farther.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Laſtly, Lord notwithſtanding all the diſcouragement I have I will Believe, Hope, and Pray till thou take me off by my own death, or the death of my Child: As I will follow on to know, and love, and ſerve the Lord, whatever thou do with me, ſo I am reſolved to Pray and Hope, and wait what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou ſay to me,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.26.</note> for I am ſure, 'tis good for a man both to hope and quietly wait for
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:108774:54"/> the Salvation of the Lord: God is worthy waiting on, even upon my Knees, I cannot be in a better excerciſe: Say then, Oh my dear Lord, I am a Sinfull worm, have a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed heart, am of polluted lips, a ſinfull life, I deſerve not the leaſt crum of Bread or drop of Water, I have forfeited my right to all Covenants, as well as common Mercys, for my ſelf and Seed: I have begot a Child in my own Image, not thine: it is a Child of wrath by nature, as well as others, but thou in thy love haſt made a Covenant with believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and their Seed: thou haſt brought me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bond of the Covenant: the like mercy I beg for mine: my Child muſt have thine Image as well as mine, or it is undone for ever: and it is not in my power to convey it, but thou canſt: My dayly errand to the throne of Grace, is to beg the bleſſings of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace to me and mine: I will not go from thy door without an alms: thou ſhalt have a troubleſom gueſt of me till thou grant my requeſt: <hi>O remember thy word unto thy ſervant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.49.</note> 
                  <hi>upon which thou haſt cauſed me to hope:</hi> Come, Lord, let Covenant-Grace enter into the ſoul of my Child, which is part of my ſelf: and I will take it as done to my ſelf; if I had not the mercy I beg under a promiſe, I durſt not ask it, but thou haſt made thy ſelf a debtor, and I will put thy bond in ſuit by Faith in Prayer: Thou canſt not deny thine own hand writing: Thou art Faithfull, and wilſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it to ſome, and why not to me.</p>
               <p>God loves ſuch importunate beggers, and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:108774:55"/> our dear Lord Jeſus hath propounded two pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables to provoke importunity:<note place="margin">Luke. 11.5, 8, 9.18.1.8.</note> therefore it is not unmannerly ſaucineſs, but holy earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and approved impudence, wherein God much delights: the End thereof is not to move God to alter his purpoſe, but that our own Souls may have the condition of thy Promiſe: thus the <hi>Canaanitiſh</hi> (or the <hi>Syrophenician</hi>) Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man crys out for her Daughter, <hi>Have mercy on me O Lord, thou Son of David, my Daughter is grievouſly vexed with a Devil.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 7.24, 25.</note> Mat. 15.22, 28. She received a firſt, a ſecond, a third re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe, but She hangs on ſtill, and will have no nay and at laſt obtained her ſuit with an high Encomium and larg grant: <hi>O Woman great is thy Faith be it unto thee even as thou wilt:</hi> go thou and do likewiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Alas! Sir but I am faithleſs, had I Faith as that Woman had, I might prevail, and you ſay Faith in Gods Covenant is neceſſary for the parent, but I cannot Pray in Faith for my Child, and how then ſhould I prevail?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> There is a two-fold faith, General, and Objective, by which you believe God is able and willing, to make good his Covenant, doth make it good to ſome, and would to thee if thou hadſt the condition: this is abſolutly neceſſary in all that come to God, and this thou haſt thou art ſure that Chriſt <hi>is able to ſave to the uttermoſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.6. Jam. 1.6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>all that come to God by him,</hi> Heb. 7.25. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to the uttermoſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> to the utmoſt extent of the Covenant-grant, yea, ſaiſt thou, I believe his ability, but I queſtion my right coming, therefore, 2.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:108774:55"/> There is a particular perſuaſion, that God will grant this requeſt, <hi>Ergo,</hi> for this child, or in this caſe: 'tis true ſometimes the Lord doth impreſs this upon the Spirit with power that this Mercy ſhall be granted, this Child ſhall be Converted, but this is not neceſſary for the obtaining of the Mercy: a godly Soul may want faith to believe the iſſue of his Prayer, and yet be heard, as you ſee in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Pſal.</hi> 31.22. <hi>I ſaid in my haſt, I am cut off from before thine eyes.</hi> Mark it, he had no particular faith for his preſervation, yet he prayed ſtill nevertheleſs. Saith he, <hi>Thou heardeſt the voyce of my ſupplication, when I cryed unto thee.</hi> Obſerve it, the want of his Faith hindred not the fruit of his Prayer, nor will it do of thine.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What ailes thee to follow ſo hard af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God? Is it not a principle of Faith? Haſt thou not laid hold on Gods Covenant for thine own Soul? What means that frequent renewing of thy Covenant with the Lord, in taking God to be thy God, chiefeſt Good, and utmoſt End? and thy dedicating thy all to the Lord? This ſhews thou art in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: for this is the Eſſence of ſaving Faith; and thy being ſo much concerned for thy Seed, declares plainly thy being in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Thou goeſt daily to the Lord, in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt pleadings for thy Children, and wilt not be beat off, (like the foreſaid woman) though one while he anſwers not, another while he gives diſcouraging anſwers: And is not this ſincere faith? Our Lord accounted it ſo in
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:108774:56"/> the woman that weathered out ſo many af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts in her importunate pleas: And are not thy motions ſtill more vigorous? Poor ſoul, thou art following the Lord with tears, ſighs, and groans, for thy wandring Child, ſaying ſtill,<note place="margin">Mar. 9.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord I believe, help thou my unbelief!</hi> I will ſtill expreſs my deſires of Grace for my child, or children; nothing elſe ſhall ſerve my turn: Civility will not pleaſe me, nor profit them without Sanctity I am not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied with Gifts without Grace; Common Grace, without Saving Grace. Carnal men are well content to ſee their Children Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Ingenious, Induſtrious, and likely to thrive in the World, good Husbands, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Tradesmen, and likely to come to preferment. But oh my Lord, thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt my breathings; I look further: My ſoul longs for a principle of Grace, and a Portion in another World: This is all my deſire, and all my Salvation.</p>
               <p>Yea, you'l ſay, But I am afraid I offend God, by being too importunate; Who can tell whether my Child be Elected, and if not, it's in vain to pray, I cannot alter Gods Decree?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 29.29</note>I Anſwer: <hi>The ſecret things belong unto the Lord our God, but thoſe things that are reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, belong unto us, and to our Children for ever, that we may do all the words of this Law.</hi> You muſt not make Gods hidden Councels, but his holy Scriptures the Rule of your Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.4.</note> God ſaith, <hi>he will have all men ſaved:</hi> Thus his Will is manifeſted, and I told you the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:108774:56"/> Warrant you have to believe, and pray for the Children of the Covenant; and you cannot be too importunate, ſo as you do not limit the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and as longas there is life, there is hope; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore continue your Prayers the term of your natural life, unleſs God take you off by ſome remarkable Providence. I knew a very gracious zealous woman, many years ago, who was weeping and wreſtling with God, in an Out-houſe in the night, for the precious Soul of her Prodigal Son, who was now fallen ſick, and upon his, Death bed; and while ſhe was groaning out her ſoul with tears, and ſtrong cryes, ſhe thought ſhe heard a voyce, ſaying to her, <hi>[Be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, what I have done I have done:]</hi> She roſe off her knees, could not ſpeak a word more, went away quieted; and upon enquiry, found that her Son breathed out his laſt breath at that very inſtant in a Town two miles thence.</p>
               <p>I am not credulous of ſuch Storys: but have great reaſon to believe the truth of it, yet the inſtance is ſingular; However this is a truth, that God ſhuts up the Spirit of Prayer, when he doth not intend to hear a good Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſo God had never denyed what ſhe had asked of God in Prayer: One objected a child of hers dying, ſhe replyed it's true, but I could never Pray for that Child; Gods aſſiſtings or withdrawings often portend the event.</p>
               <p>But 'tis ſafeſt for us to ſuſpect ſome fault in our Perſons or Prayers if God do not hear us for our Children, therefore it becomes us to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:108774:57"/> ſearch our Conſciences and Converſations, to find out the Sin, confeſs it, beg a pardon in the Blood of Chriſt, and Mortify it, and then Pray, ſay as Divine <hi>Herbert</hi>'s <hi>Church Lock and Key.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I know it is my Sin, which locks thine ears, and binds thy hands</l>
                     <l>Out-crying my requeſts, drowning my tears,</l>
                     <l>Or elſe the chilneſs of my faint demands:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But as cold hands are angry with the Fire, and mend it ſtill.</l>
                     <l>So I do lay the want of my deſire,</l>
                     <l>Not on my Sins or coldneſs but thy will:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yet hear, Oh God! only for his bloods ſake, which pleads for me.</l>
                     <l>For though ſins plead too, yet like ſtones they make,</l>
                     <l>His bloods ſweet current much more loud to be.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:108774:57"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
